<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog.atom"/>
  <title>Film Drives - BLOG</title>
  <updated>2020-06-01T16:55:00+10:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Film Drives</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/hands-on-with-arriraw-hde</id>
    <published>2020-06-01T16:55:00+10:00</published>
    <updated>2020-06-07T16:05:05+10:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/hands-on-with-arriraw-hde"/>
    <title>HANDS ON WITH ARRIRAW HDE</title>
    <author>
      <name>Bradley Andrew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[I think ARRI and Codex have done a good job of putting together technical explanations of the new <a href="https://x2x.media/codex-hde" target="_blank" title="Codex HDE" rel="noopener noreferrer">ARRIRAW HDE Format</a> and how it works. This has been instrumental in getting Producers, Directors and DPs to utilise it for their production. Technical explanations aside, that doesn't mean people understand how to execute HDE on-set. Over the past few months I've had many inquiries about HDE and how it can be practically implemented, this includes, how do we do HDE, what needs to be enabled, is it a camera setting, what are the problems, will it work with my operating system, etc.
<p>I've got many HDE Jobs under my belt now, all of them TVCs ranging from bigger 16 Day TVCs to smaller two day jobs. I've run different versions of Codex Device Manager (V5.0 and V5.1 BETA) in different versions of macOS (Mojave 10.14 and Catalina 10.15) on different computers (MacBook Pro and Custom Built 'iMac Pro' Hackintosh) with different Cameras and Codex Hardware (Alexa Mini, Alexa LF and Alexa Mini LF). I've been in touch with ARRI and Codex about HDE Issues as well as liaising with Pomfort and Imagine Products about software specific problems and discrepancies.  With that experience on hand, I have decided to put together this comprehensive post on all things HDE. I trust it will serve as a useful tool for you.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>ESSENTIAL INFO</strong></span></h1>
<p>Rather than re-hashing all of the information that ARRI and Codex have provided, I would recommend that you take a read of their resources first before diving into this blog post.</p>
<p>For ARRI's explanation of HDE you can reference their FAQ and select HDE / High Density Encoding from the dropdown:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.arri.com/en/learn-help/learn-help-camera-system/frequently-asked-questions/arriraw-faq" target="_blank" title="ARRI HDE EXPLANATION" rel="noopener noreferrer">ARRI EXPLANATION LINK</a></p>
<p>For Codex's explanation of HDE you can reference their dedicated HDE Page, the Spiderman Case Study is well worth a read:</p>
<p><a href="https://x2x.media/codex-hde" target="_blank" title="CODEX HDE EXPLANATION" rel="noopener noreferrer">CODEX EXPLANATION LINK</a></p>
<p>As a very brief summary, HDE is a new recording format introduced by ARRI and Codex in 2019. It applies compression to the ARRIRAW Recording Format, this is done on your computer while offloading, not on the camera. Think of this compression in the same way that you ZIP a file on your computer. The computer processes the data and compresses the files, meaning they become smaller in size and require less storage capacity on your hard drives (HDDs) or solid state drives (SSDs). HDE works like zipping a file in terms of file integrity, the ARRIRAW becomes smaller in size without any quality loss. HDE Files actually do not exist until the compression is done, just like a ZIP File doesn’t exist until the compression is done and the .zip file is created. Given that the HDE Compression is done while offloading the data, this means that the files do not exist until they are offloaded. They do exist as normal ARRIRAW on the camera media but they do not exist as ARRIRAW HDE, this is a seperate version of the footage that is created while offloading.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="ARI to ARX Diagram" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ARI_to_ARX_Diagram_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590970676" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>On average, the compression offered by HDE equates a 40% data saving. I found it to be around 35% but I have certainly seen instances of it compressing the data by 50%, calling it a 40% saving seems fair. This means that on average, 1TB of ARRIRAW becomes 600GB of ARRIRAW HDE, that's a massive data saving, especially over the course of a longer job. This in turn translates to cost savings. On average SSD Storage is around $300-$350 AUD per terabyte, if you can decrease the amount of SSD Storage required you will save 40% on your drive costs. I’ve found that offloads are also quicker meaning you will save on labour. This is a win for everyone.</p>
<p>With that summary in mind and the knowledge you gained from the ARRI and Codex explanations, let's dive in.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>MY FIRST HDE JOB</strong></span></h1>
<p>In November / December 2019 I did a two week commercial using an Alexa Mini LF shooting 4.5K ARRIRAW. I was warned in advance that the Director/DP liked to shoot a lot, given we were shooting 4.5K RAW I made the call to utilise HDE on this specific job. It was no trouble getting the decision to shoot HDE over the line. The producer and director both trusted my judgement and were confident in my ability to problem solve should we encounter any issues.</p>
<p>I was running a 2018 MacBook Pro on macOS 10.14.6 (Mojave) with my <a href="https://filmdrives.com/pages/data-deluxe" target="_blank" title="Data Deluxe" rel="noopener noreferrer">Data Deluxe System</a> and utilising <a href="https://codex.online/products/device-manager" target="_blank" title="Codex Device Manager" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex Device Manager</a> 5.0 BETA (5.0.0-05325). Film Drives built some Custom SSD RAIDs for the job, our main set of drives were 2x 16TB SSD RAIDs. Should we shoot over 16TB, our overflow drives were a set of 2x 8TB SSD RAIDs.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Desktop_Setup_grande.jpg?v=1590971442" alt="Desktop Setup"></p>
<p>The 16TB SSD RAIDs consisted of 4x 4TB SATA SSDs. I didn’t want to set them up as a 4 Bay RAID 5 as I’d lose too much capacity, 16TB was already pushing it which is why we had the overflow drives. I also didn’t want to set them up as a 4 Bay RAID 0, yes, that would have given me great speed throughput but if one of the four SSDs had a problem or failed, we would lose that entire backup. Instead I opted for a nice middle ground. I created two partitions for each 16TB SSD RAID, Partition 01-1 was an 8TB RAID 0 made up from two of the four 4TB SSDs, Partition 01-2 was an 8TB RAID 0 made up from the remaining two 4TB SSDs.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="4 Bay RAID" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/4_Bay_RAID_grande.jpg?v=1590971275" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>I did tests prior to shooting to determine how the drives would perform. When setup as a 4 Bay 16TB RAID 0 Partition my speed tests using <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/blackmagic-disk-speed-test/id425264550?mt=12" target="_blank" title="Blackmagic Disk Speed Test" rel="noopener noreferrer">Blackmagic Disk Speed Test</a> were 1180MB/s Write and 1375MB/s Read. When setup as 2x 2 Bay 8TB RAID 0 Partitions, each partition performed at 915MB/s Write and 985MB/s Read. The speed difference between 2x 2 Bay 8TB RAID 0 Partitions averaged to be 26% slower than the 4 Bay 16TB RAID 0 Partition, given the added safety of having two partitions this felt like a good trade-off to me.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="SSD RAID Speed Comparison" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/4_BAY_vs._2_BAY_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590982969" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>This TVC was a travel job, we set off around Australia with our first few days of shooting being up north in Darwin and Kununurra to do some aerial work. Given the nature of working in a helicopter only the Director/DP, the Gimbal Technician and the Helicopter Pilot could be up in the air. In terms of data management, this meant they would shoot a whole lot while in the air, land back at base at the end of the day and hand over many full cards of footage. This is where my work began.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Helicopter Prep Work" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Helicopter_Prep_grande.jpg?v=1590972883" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>At the end of shoot day one we’d shot close to 1.4TB of ARRIRAW, this is not all that much and actually served me well as my first on-job execution of HDE. I had a bunch of different software on-hand to try out and see which served me best. Given this was Shoot Day 01 of an 11 Day Shoot spread over two weeks, it was important to get it right now so that the rest of the job would be as smooth as possible.</p>
<p><strong>The software I was using is listed below:</strong></p>
<p>Shotput Pro 2019.3.2 (Current Version as of 23/11/19)<br>Silverstack (Current Version as of 23/11/19)<br>Offload Manager (V1.1.1 Build 27)<br>Hedge (19.5α Build 787)</p>
<p>As regular ARRIRAW the card came in at 958GB. If you factor in the 40% data saving of HDE, I was expecting the ARRIRAW HDE version of this card to be 575GB. Offloading 575GB to my drives that perform at 915MB/s Write, my estimate was that an offload and verify would take 30-40 Minutes. I did the same offload of Roll H001 as HDE on each software, below you will find what I have noted:</p>
<p><strong>Shotput Pro 2019.3.2</strong></p>
<p>Shotput Pro 2019.3.2 took 55:56 Minutes to offload and verify. It then got stuck on ‘Generating Reports’ for 30 Minutes at which point I quit the software. In the past I have found image sequences to take a long time when it comes to generating a PDF Report in Shotput Pro as it tries to take a frame grab for each and every frame to put into the report. Whenever dealing with image sequences and using Shotput Pro I disable PDF Reporting and only use TXT Reporting, that is what I had enabled in this instance yet I still had a massive lag come reporting time. The final byte count in Finder when using the Get Info Function of macOS came in at 579,512,806,159 bytes.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Shotput Pro Report Settings" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Shotput_Pro_Report_Settings_grande.jpg?v=1590973678" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>One thing worth flagging is that during the offload, Shotput Pro gives you a readout of ‘Bytes to Read’ and ‘Bytes Read’. After the offload had finished and Shotput was onto the verification process there was a mismatch between these two values. I wasn’t sure what to make of this at the time but it did raise a red flag with me as normally these two numbers match.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Shotput Pro Bytes Read Mismatch" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SPP_STABLE_BytesReadMismatch_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590973244" style="float: none;"></p>
<p><strong>Silverstack</strong></p>
<p>Silverstack took 35:21 Minutes to offload and verify. This was pleasing as it was the first offload that sat within my estimated range. The final byte count in Finder was 579,512,891,062 bytes. One thing worth noting is a warning message within Silverstack when I initiated a HDE Offload. A screengrab of the warning message is below.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Silverstack HDE Warning Message" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Silverstack_Warning_Message_grande.jpg?v=1590973373" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>The wording wasn’t 100% clear to me but what I believe it is trying to say is this:</p>
<p>‘The HDE files that we will create are different from the ARRIRAW Files you are copying from, we don’t know exactly what the file output will be as things will be discovered as the offload takes place, note this and double check that all clips that exist on the original card are copied to your destinations’.</p>
<p>I was already operating with a great deal of scrutiny when it comes to HDE so it’s nice to have a warning that reminds you to be extra pedantic.</p>
<p><strong>Offload Manager</strong></p>
<p>Offload Manager took 20:02 Minutes to offload and 19:10 Minutes to verify. The final byte count in Finder was 579,512,806,159 bytes. This was a touch slower than the offload and verify operation in Silverstack, I suspect this stems from the difference in how each software processes tasks. Silverstack works file by file, H001C001 will be offloaded then verified, then Silverstack will move onto H001C002 and repeat the process. Offload Manager will offload all of the clips first, then do a verification pass running the checksum operation. I was pleased with the performance of Offload Manager as it sat within my estimated range.</p>
<p><strong>Hedge</strong></p>
<p>Hedge took 50:47 Minutes to offload and give the tick of approval. I then studied Activity Monitor and watched Hedge perform additional reads and deeper verification in the background for 11:14 Minutes. In total I would call the complete Hedge offload and verify 62:01 Minutes. The final byte count in Finder was 579,512,806,159 bytes. For more information on how Hedge’s Verification differs to that of Shotput Pro, Silverstack and Offload Manager I suggest you check out my blog post on <a href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/what-is-the-fastest-offload-software" target="_blank" title="What Is The Fastest Offload Software?" rel="noopener noreferrer">‘What Is The Fastest Offload Software?’</a>.</p>
<p><strong>When you compare the results this is how it looks for speed:</strong></p>
<p>Shotput Pro - 55:56 Mins<br>Silverstack - 35:21 Mins<br>Offload Manager - 39:12 Mins<br>Hedge - 62:01 Mins (50:47 Mins if you don’t count the background verification)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Offload Software Time Comparison" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Offload_Software_Time_Graph_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590982260" style="float: none;"></p>
<p><strong>When you compare the results this is how it looks for byte size:</strong></p>
<p>Shotput Pro - 579,512,806,159 bytes<br>Silverstack - 579,512,891,062 bytes<br>Offload Manager - 579,512,806,159 bytes<br>Hedge - 579,512,806,159 bytes</p>
<p>It should be noted that my estimate for this card was 575GB of ARRIRAW. All software offloads came in at 579GB which is close to the estimate. HDE turned this card from 958GB of data to 579GB of data. This is a 379GB saving which equates to 39.5%, very close to the specced 40% claimed by ARRI.</p>
<p>Speed is speed and faster is usually better, obviously there is some very different processing going on between each software that equates to better performance in one as opposed to the other. This could be on the individual software level and in how they implement the ARRIRAW SDK provided by ARRI.</p>
<p>What concerned me more was the mild difference in byte size. Codex Device Manager works to compress and create the .ARX Files from the .ARI Files and the Offload Software copies the newly created HDE FIles to your destinations. In theory, all software should process HDE the same. That means that the HDE Version of H001C001 that is copied with Shotput Pro should be identical to the HDE Version of H001C001 copied by Hedge. In my case this was true for Shotput Pro, Offload Manager and Hedge, but the Silverstack offload had a slightly different byte count. This could be caused by differences in the binary and metric calculation of data or it could be a hidden file created by macOS.</p>
<p>I was working under a high degree of caution as HDE was a new format for me, I couldn’t put that difference in bytes found in Silverstack down to coincidence and I didn’t have time to investigate further. Given the report generation issues I had with Shotput Pro and the burden on my mind when it came to factoring in the Hedge background verification, it seemed that Offload Manager was the best choice. Offload Manager also offered faster performance than Shotput Pro and Hedge in my tests, with that in mind I decided that Offload Manager was the best choice for the remainder of this job.</p>
<p>I felt good about Offload Manager but there was still one thing that bothered me about HDE. The ARRIRAW Files for H001 were 958GB, the HDE Files for H001 were 579GB, the only tool in the workflow for ensuring that the HDE Files were indeed a compressed version of the ARRIRAW Files was the offloading software. What if the software made a mistake? Very unlikely but it’s a check I generally like to implement in all of my offloads. Typically I will offload and verify with a software, then I use ‘Get Info’ in Finder to check the byte size of all destinations and the original, if they match great, that’s a second check, if there is a mismatch I look closer and determine why there is a mismatch in the byte count. I feel this is a great way to double check your offload software and there isn’t anyway to do this with HDE. I have developed a workflow for dealing with HDE which employs a reasonable way to work around this problem which I will detail in a seperate blog post.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="HDE Get Info Comparison" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Get_Info_Comparison_grande.jpg?v=1590974215" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>After committing to Offload Manager, the rest of the aerials went off without a hitch. The software performed reliably and at consistent speeds. I felt good once I had developed some logical tests to crosscheck my HDE workflow, all was happy days. This took me up to Shoot Day 03, we wrapped aerials and sent our H Camera Body back to the rental house. We flew to Adelaide and started the next leg of our shoot which entailed a much bigger crew than the splinter aerial unit. Along with new crew, we had a new camera body which was the start of many HDE headaches.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>HDE ISSUES</strong></span></h1>
<p>We added A Camera to our lineup which was another Alexa Mini LF Body prepped in Melbourne and brought over to Adelaide. The first scene on the A Camera was a sunset shot which meant a very similar situation to the helicopter work. We’d prep, shoot nothing, then the light would be right and we’d shoot a lot. Most of my work would be done on wrap. I chatted with the 2nd AC and we were able to get a camera reload in while changing setups which was very useful.</p>
<p>I got back to my data station which was setup off set and inserted the first card into the Codex Reader. No response. No lights, no flashing, no sounds. What was going on here? I know my computer works as I had used it perfectly fine the day before with the H Camera. What was new in this setup, the camera body, the cards and the card reader. The easiest thing to troubleshoot was the card reader so I swapped out the USB-C Cable to see if that would help, no change, I tried it on different USB-C Ports, no change, I tried it with no other devices connected, simply power and card reader just encase it was a bus power issue, still no change.</p>
<p>While I was troubleshooting they had wrapped on set so I went back to collect the second card of the day and a spare card to use for troubleshooting. While I popped out to collect this I thought I’d leave the first card plugged into the reader just encase it needed a little bit of time to fire up. To my surprise, when I got back to the data station after collecting the other cards from set, the first card had mounted. Weird.</p>
<p>I proceeded with a HDE Offload via Offload Manager and all seemed to be going fine. Just as the offload was coming up on being done it threw an error. The error message was ‘Unexpected Abort During Write. (110)’. To me this meant that either the card or one of the drives ejected themselves while the offload was happening. What I would normally do in this instance is clear the original failed offload and try again. When I tried the HDE Offload again it failed with the exact same error message, I was watching it this time, there were no disconnects, both drives and the card were connected the entire time.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="A001 Error on Offload Manager" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/A001_Error_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590974771" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>My next step of troubleshooting was to eject all devices, reboot the computer and try again. When the computer booted I plugged in both drives, they showed up no worries, I ran a speed test on them with <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/blackmagic-disk-speed-test/id425264550?mt=12" target="_blank" title="Blackmagic Disk Speed Test" rel="noopener noreferrer">Blackmagic Disk Speed Test</a>, they were working as expected. I plugged in the card reader with the first card A001, same as last time it didn’t mount right away but I knew it eventually would. After three minutes of waiting the mag mounted, this delay was strange, the card would be inserted and there would be literally no response at all, then suddenly the lights would flash, the fans would spin up and the card would mount to my desktop. Now that I was good to go I tried the offload again. Same place, the error occurred. After three failed HDE attempts it was time to shift my approach, I couldn’t keep wasting productions time as I was well and truly into overtime at this point.</p>
<p>I had a friend encounter a similar issue a few weeks prior on a different job, he never got to the bottom of it and his solution was to do a regular ARRIRAW Offload instead so that’s what I tried. I went to Codex Device Manager and disabled HDE, the card still took a while to mount but it mounted as a normal ARRIRAW Partition. I offloaded the card and there were no issues. Given the suspect behaviour of this card I paid very close attention when performing my Quality Control (QC) Checks. Went I was satisfied that all was safe and sound I moved onto the second mag of the day. I re-enabled HDE in Codex Device Manager and inserted A002, it mounted right away. I proceeded with the HDE Offload and it worked as expected.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="HDE Toggle" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/HDE_Toggle_grande.jpg?v=1590975396" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>A001 failed in all sorts of ways, but A002 worked exactly the same as all of the cards from H Camera. What this said to me is that there was a problem with the first card. This was good news, I had suspected the problem may have been with the card reader and we were very rural, getting a replacement sent to Outback South Australia would prove quite difficult. For the moment I quarantined that card intending not to use it again, I then reached out to Codex and ARRI to tell them of what happened and see if there was any help that they could offer. Thus the situation evolved.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>TWO ISSUES, NOT ONE</strong></span></h1>
<p>After extensively chatting with Codex and ARRI it became clear that I was dealing with two seperate issues, not one.</p>
<p><strong>Issue #01</strong><br>Codex Compact Drives Taking Several Minutes to Mount<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Issue #02</strong><br>Failed HDE Offloads<strong> </strong></p>
<p>I initially thought these two issues went hand in hand, the team from Codex pointed out otherwise and in my testing I found it to be true. I had instances later on in the job where I would have a card exhibit the slow mount issue but then perform a successful HDE Offload.  After other extensive testing I discovered that the slow mount happens only after the card has been used by the camera. If I have already waited through the slow mount and read files from the card, then I eject it, then re-insert it, the card will mount quickly as normal. Note that this is different behaviour to that first A001 Card that I had problems with. If I clear the card on the computer, put it back in the camera, format the card in the camera, shoot on it and then insert it into the computer the slow mount will occur again. It seems to just happen on that first mount after each format on camera for specific cards.</p>
<p>Codex informed me they were aware of the slow mount issue and were working to reproduce and understand what is going on. I ended up narrowing down the slow mount issue to just two cards from our kit, Iater on when the job finished I believe these were sent back to Codex for testing and replaced with new units.</p>
<p>As for the second issue, failed HDE offloads, that requires a bit more explaining, let’s dive in.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong> FAILED HDE OFFLOADS </strong></span></h1>
<p>Codex informed me that when a clip fails to offload as HDE it is likely a CRC Checksum Issue. What does that mean? Every single frame of ARRIRAW that gets recorded has a CRC Checksum which corresponds to that individual frame. A checksum will compare one value of data to another, giving an all clear when the data matches. In this instance the ARRI Cameras are checking that the data created by the camera sensor matches the data that gets written to the camera card. This way we ensure the data doesn’t change while being internally transmitted from the sensor to the card. This CRC Checksum between the sensor and the card is often called an Image Essence Checksum as it works to make sure what we see while shooting is what gets recorded to our card.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="CRC Check Diagram" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CRC_Diagram_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590976568" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>If the CRC Checksum that is created by the camera sensor has one value and the CRC Checksum created by the camera card has another value we have a mismatch. This means what the sensor captured is not what has been written to the card. Codex informed me that the Codex Device Manager V5.0 BETA Software used a fast-fail method, this means that if a clip has a CRC Mismatch on any frame it will fail to offload as ARRIRAW HDE.</p>
<p>Let’s think about this. We were shooting at 25fps, so if we shot a clip that ran for 40 Seconds that would be 1000 Frames and thus 1000 CRC Checksums of the Image Essence. If any 1 out of those 1000 checksums had a mismatch I can’t offload that clip as HDE. Say I shot 10 Clips of the same length on that card, that’s 10,000 Frames and thus 10,000 CRC Checksums of the Image Essence. If any one of those ten thousand checksums had a mismatch I can’t offload that card as HDE.</p>
<p>Codex informed me that a CRC Mismatch can occur when the camera loses power during recording. I can understand how this may happen in rare circumstances on set. On this job the camera never lost power while recording but I still had CRC Mismatches on 14 Rolls out of the 55 Rolls that we shot on A Camera. Given the high frequency of the issue perhaps there was a firmware issue with the camera. I sent the camera logs to ARRI and the software logs to Codex which helped to troubleshoot things on their end but I didn’t hear if there were any problems camera side. Regardless, we were in the middle of a job in outback Australia with a bunch of travel, not an ideal time to update your camera’s firmware especially without a backup camera body, thus we had to persist.</p>
<p>What did that mean for me? Well, ideally I’d like to find a way to determine if a particular card had a CRC Mismatch before I started offloading it. As it currently stood I would start a card as a HDE Offload and the offload would process. If a HDE Mismatch was present it would fail towards the end of the offload, that would be my first indication of a problem. Then I’d eject the card, turn off HDE, re-insert the card and offload it as regular ARRIRAW. The time wasted processing a HDE Offload that was destined to fail wasn’t ideal, for full 1TB cards this could equate to 20-25 Mins of time lost. So I tried to find an alternate way.</p>
<p><strong>Method #01<br></strong><strong>ARRI Meta Extract GUI</strong></p>
<p>Codex informed me that ARRI Meta Extract is capable of running CRC Checks on clips so I decided to give that a go. You have two options when using ARRI Meta Extract, you can tailor it to just focus on CRC Checks or you can set it to process all metadata. I tried both and in both instances the software gave me accurate CRC Check information.</p>
<p>For a successful clip it would display something like:<br>’Finished (CRC Check): Verified 1035/1035. Mismatch: 0’</p>
<p>For a failed clip it would display something like:<br>’Finished (CRC Check): Verified 4839/4841. Mismatch: 2’</p>
<p>The software shows you this information visually and also outputs a .csv file for each clip. If you were to interpret the data for the failed clip you would see that the clip has 4841 Frames, 4839 Frames were okay but two frames had issues, thus the whole clip fails the CRC Image Essence Check.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="ARRI Meta Extract - GUI Version" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ARRI_Metadata_Extract_GUI_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590976972" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>While running this is useful, practically it didn’t help me. A process I trialed was to insert a card into my computer, then to run a CRC Check via ARRI Metadata Extract. If the CRC Check came back good I would proceed with an ARRIRAW HDE Offload, if the CRC Check Failed then I would proceed with a regular ARRIRAW Offload. The problem was that running a CRC Check via ARRI Meta Extract on the entire card took the same time as offloading the entire card with Offload Manager.</p>
<p>Say I have a card that takes 30 Mins to offload as HDE, I found that if I offloaded that same card as regular ARRIRAW it would take 50 Mins to offload. There are a few ways this could play out:</p>
<p><strong>Option #01:</strong> <br>CRC Check in ARRI Meta Extract (30 Mins) -&gt; CRC Fail -&gt; Regular ARRIRAW Offload in Offload Manager (50 Mins)</p>
<p><strong>Option #02:</strong> <br>CRC Check in ARRI Meta Extract (30 Mins) -&gt; CRC Good -&gt; HDE Offload in Offload Manager (30 Mins)</p>
<p><strong>Option #03:</strong> <br>Failed HDE Offload in Offload Manager (15-20 Mins) - &gt; Regular ARRIRAW Offload in Offload Manager (50 Mins)</p>
<p><strong>Option #04:</strong> <br>HDE Offload in Offload Manager (30 Mins)</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ARRI_Meta_Extract_Graph_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590985605" alt="ARRI Meta Extract Graph"></p>
<p> </p>
<p>Option 01 and Option 03 represent when a HDE Offload Fails. Option 02 and Option 04 represent a successful HDE Offload. For both outcomes I was better off time wise to try and fail a HDE Offload in Offload Manager than I was to run a CRC Check with ARRI Meta Extract followed by the appropriate offload. This led me to my second option.</p>
<p><strong>Method #02<br></strong><strong>ARRI Meta Extract CMD</strong></p>
<p>This is the same ARRI Meta Extract Software except it runs in the command line rather than having a graphical user interface. I thought that maybe some of the front end processing slowed down the CRC Checks that the software was performing. This wasn’t the case. The CRC Checks took the same amount of time in the CMD Version (Command Line) as it did in the GUI Version (Graphical User Interface).</p>
<p>This is a PDF Export of what you can expect in macOS Terminal when using ARRI Meta Extract via the Command Line:</p>
<p><a href="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CRC_CMD.pdf?v=1590977365" target="_blank" title="ARRI Meta Extract - Command Line" rel="noopener noreferrer">AME CMD Export</a></p>
<p>I also read in some documentation that a specific ARRIRAW CRC Check Tool exists. This being a specific software tool that is seperate from Meta Extract. I couldn’t find this tool online and did chase it up with ARRI but never ended up getting my hands on the tool.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="ARRI CRC Check Tool" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CRC_Check_Tool_grande.jpg?v=1590977511" style="float: none;"></p>
<p><strong>Method #03<br></strong><strong>Offload Manager HDE Fail</strong></p>
<p>As eluded to above, this is where I would run a HDE Offload first and monitor to see if it fails due to a CRC Mismatch. If it fails then I would cancel the HDE Offload and start a new offload of the regular ARRIRAW Footage. If it didn’t fail then great, things are working as they should and I have a super speedy offload. What I didn’t like about this method is that it’s a wildcard, it introduced a bit of anxiety into my workflow as I was constantly hoping that the offload would work. However I did find that I was able to make this method more efficient, the downside was that it meant more hands on work and thus extra time.</p>
<p>Rather than using the standard view in Offload Manager to check the progress of my offload, you can right click the offload that is in progress and select ‘Show Job Details for This Offload’. In this detailed view you can monitor the offload and the verify progress on a clip by clip basis. This meant that if I had a card that had 49 Clips on it and the clip with the CRC Mismatch was C023, rather than waiting until C049 to finish copying to discover the issue I could now monitor the offload in real-time and see the issue occur as the software processed C023. Once I see that error I cancel the HDE Offload and start a new offload as regular ARRIRAW. Using this method I reduced wasted offloading time by around 50-60% at the cost of being close to the computer during the copy process. A worthy tradeoff.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Offload Manager Job View" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Offload_Manager_Job_View_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590985958" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>You might be wondering why I don’t process cards in segments with partial offloads. Say I have a card with 20 Clips and only one clip fails the CRC Check. In theory I could process 19 Clips as HDE and just that one failed clip as regular ARRIRAW. Yes, this is a possibility but it feels messy. Editorial was fine with me doing whole cards as ARRIRAW and whole cards as ARRIRAW HDE depending on the CRC Mismatch Issue, but once you start chopping cards up and processing them clip by clip the risk of making a mistake increases, not to mention the time cost of parsing which clips were good for HDE and which clips were not.</p>
<p>I was leaving a digital note on the drives detailing each card that had a CRC Issue and thus needed to be processed as regular ARRIRAW. Given that HDE was very new at the time I wanted to make sure editorial understood what was going on. Should the drives be used down the line, be it in a few months or many years in the future, it’s important to have a clear paper trail outlining anything that deviates from normal. I don’t want a call in 7 Months time from someone asking why some clips have HDE at the end and why others don’t, best to leave clear details of what happened and why with an explanation of what you did to solve the issue.</p>
<p>For the rest of the job I utilised Method #03 detailed above. Whenever I had a successful HDE Offload it was a relief as I had many HDE fails even up until the last shooting day. I always just hoped that the issue didn’t occur on the last card of the day, meaning extra time to finish the days work and thus less sleep as we were working on fairly tight turnarounds.</p>
<p>I came out of that job with the opinion that HDE is great but not perfect. The data, time and cost savings are fantastic but some issues are yet to be ironed out meaning it requires a lot of baby sitting for error free offloads. However, HDE continued to be developed having it’s bugs squashed and issues sorted. I finished that job in December 2019, by March 2020 my experience with HDE had certainly improved.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>CODEX DEVICE MANAGER V5.1 BETA</strong></span></h1>
<p>In Feb 2020 Codex realised the long awaited V5.1 of Codex Device Manager as a Public Beta. I say long awaited as this version added support for macOS 10.15 (Catalina) which many users had been desperate for. Another crucial improvement introduced in this version of the software is how Codex handles the CRC Mismatch Issue. Rather than the fast-fail method of V5.0, V5.1 allows clips that have CRC Mismatch Issues to passthrough the HDE Pipeline and be offloaded as ARRIRAW HDE. Codex Device Manager will log the CRC Mismatch Errors and note them in a report. Codex have told me that the CRC Error Handling algorithm will flag the CRC Mismatch and throw an error to let you know, you can then proceed with the offload and the issue will be detailed in the Codex Log Files. Offload Software such as Silverstack, Offload Manager, Shotput Pro and Hedge will be able to implement the error logging and reporting, how it gets implemented is up to the developer as they all function slightly differently.</p>
<p>One other difference between V5.0 and V5.1 that is noteworthy is that V5.0 used OSXFUSE as it’s virtual file system while V5.1 uses X2XFUSE as it’s virtual file system. I was initially cautious of this but it has been confirmed that X2XFUSE is inclusive of the OSXFUSE Source Code. This means that you still have the same reliable foundation that you’ve known for years, just with some new tweaks built specifically by Codex. Having their own version allows Codex to tailor the virtual file system to the specific needs of Device Manager and the hardware it supports. If you wanted to have a version of OSXFUSE installed for different purposes yet still run X2XFUSE for Device Manager you can, having two versions that can co-exist is useful when dealing with compatibility issues and troubleshooting.</p>
<p>When the V5.1 Update landed I upgraded my systems to macOS 10.15.3 (Catalina) and processed to refresh my system with all up to date software. Since then I have utilised HDE on many TVCs and haven’t encountered any major problems. I’m feeling confident that Codex have ironed out the issues that plagued me on my first HDE Job. The software is still in Public Beta so I’m sure things are still being refined to make them as bulletproof as possible. The next section of this article will help you to understand any quirks of HDE that you may come across while working with it on set.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>INTERESTING QUIRKS OF HDE</strong></span></h1>
<p>As with any new technology there are new processes that need to be managed and quirks that need to monitored. HDE isn’t immune to this and I’d like to run you through some of the things I’ve noticed to date that are worth keeping an eye on.</p>
<p><strong>The 'drserver' Process</strong></p>
<p>When running any data management process I always have <a href="https://bjango.com/mac/istatmenus/" target="_blank" title="iStat Menus" rel="noopener noreferrer">iStat Menus</a> running on my Mac. It’s a great portable tool that allows you to quickly and easily glance what your computer is doing, from CPU Load to Temperature. When I was performing HDE Offloads I noticed one process that was always present when looking at iStat Menus, ‘drserver’.</p>
<p>The process ‘drserver’ is Codex’s behind the scenes brain. It seems to be handling all of the data throughput from the camera card to the computer, which of course is being mediated by the Codex Card Reader. Codex have stated that HDE is CPU dependant. The extra compression that HDE introduces needs to be processed and the computer’s CPU is what does all of the legwork.</p>
<p>During my first HDE Job I kept a keen eye on my computer’s processes as it was offloading each HDE Card. No surprise, ‘drserver’ was top of the list when looking at CPU Usage. This is expected given the CPU Heavy HDE Processing. What did surprise me was that the Internal GPU (Radeon Pro 560X in my 2018 MacBook Pro) was pretty much maxed out in terms of Memory and Processor. When I looked at which processes were using the iGPU it was an Adobe Helper, Dropbox, ScreenFlow and ‘drserver’. Why was ‘drserver’ using my GPU? It was meant to be solely CPU Dependant. I contacted Codex to try and get to the bottom of it. The problem was classified as a resource allocation issue but it’s underlying cause was unclear. Codex assured me that their software doesn’t use GPU Rendering for HDE Files and they suspected the problem may be related to a hang in CRC Handling which was part of the CRC Mismatch Issue that I was experiencing on that job.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="drserver Using GPU" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/drserver_01_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590988212" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>Remember, on that job I was using Codex Device Manager V5.0 BETA. With V5.1 of Codex Device Manager a few of the potential causes for this issue should be resolved. With V5.1 a new error handling process was introduced which will report and log errors in a more meaningful way, if you did see ‘drserver’ utilising your GPU the team at Codex will be in a better position to understand the cause of the problem. There is also a hidden configuration option that prevents ‘drserver’ from accessing any GPU resources, this can only be enabled by a Codex Engineer via a remote troubleshooting session.</p>
<p>With that in mind, I’d advise you to keep an eye on ‘drserver’ while you are offloading. See how much CPU it’s using and if it’s tapping any GPU Resources at all. If there is something that seems out of the ordinary please touch base with Codex Support.</p>
<p><strong>Offload Speeds | HDE vs. Regular ARRIRAW<br></strong></p>
<p>During my first HDE job I had a chance to compare offload speeds between a HDE Offload and a Regular ARRIRAW Offload.  You’ll recall that my SSD RAIDs performed at 915MB/s Write and 985MB/s Read when tested with <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/blackmagic-disk-speed-test/id425264550?mt=12" target="_blank" title="Blackmagic Disk Speed Test" rel="noopener noreferrer">Blackmagic Disk Speed Test</a>.</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Regular ARRIRAW</span><strong><br></strong>When offloading Regular ARRIRAW I could see Offload Manager reading around 930MB/s from the Codex Mag and writing 1800MB/s to my two SSD RAIDs. When verifying, Offload Manager would be reading between 1800MB/s - 2700MB/s. These numbers line up when you assume a base offload speed of 900MB/s. The verify process varied pending if Offload Manager was reading from my two destination drives or two destination drives plus the original camera media.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Non HDE Offload and Verify" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Non_HDE_Offload_and_Verify_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590988901" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>Please note from the screen grabs above the CPU Usage. When doing a regular ARRIRAW Offload or verify the CPU Usage is very low.</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">HDE ARRIRAW</span><strong><br></strong>When offloading HDE ARRIRAW I could see ‘drserver’ reading around 780MB/s from the Codex Mag and Offload Manager writing around 900MB/s to my SSD RAIDs. When verifying, ‘drserver’ was reading around 780MB/s from the Codex Mag and Offload Manager was reading around 1800MB/s from my SSD RAIDs, this is in line with what I would expect for verification of two destination drives plus the original camera media.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="HDE Offload and Verify" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/HDE_Offload_and_Verify_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590989209" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>Please note from the screen grabs above the CPU Usage. When doing a HDE ARRIRAW Offload or verify the CPU Usage is very high.</p>
<p><strong>Offload Speeds | Comparison</strong></p>
<p>What shocked me about these results is that a HDE Offload seemed slower solely when looking at sheer data throughput. The Codex Mag could be read at 780MB/s via HDE while the same mag could be read at 900MB/s via regular ARRIRAW.</p>
<p>In real life HDE performing slower was a non-issue as the amount of data and time saved by HDE (40%) outweighed the data throughput handicap we could observe. This means that offloading 600GB at 780MB/s is faster than offloading 1000GB at 900MB/s. Still what was causing the handicap? This is where thermal load comes into play. Sometimes it feels like technology’s biggest battle is with heat dissipation. When something gets too hot it’s performance will throttle to stop heat from destroying it’s components. This is commonly referred to as ‘thermal throttling’, it happens with SSDs and CPUs.</p>
<p><strong>Offload Speeds | Thermal Throttling</strong></p>
<p>So which was maxing out here? The thermal load on the SSD RAIDs can be ruled out as each drive performed at 900MB/s for both regular ARRIRAW and HDE ARRIRAW. It comes down to the SSD within the Codex Mag or the CPU within my MacBook Pro. I didn’t have any external thermometers on hand to measure the Codex Mag or Reader, nor did I have an internal readout on it’s temperature. However I did have a readout on my CPUs Temperature which can be loosely observed via iStat Menus in the screenshot below. The highlighted top left number is indicative of the CPU Proximity Temperature Sensor, which is sitting at 97°C. The CPU that is being used within my MacBook Pro has a T Junction of 100°C, this means that the max temperature the CPU can hit is 100°C, once it hits this number the performance of the CPU will be throttled. The system will only throttle the CPU when the MacBook Pro can not cool the CPU effectively. The inability to effectively cool itself is a well known issue for MacBook Pros, particularly in the newer style USB-C MacBook Pros. I suspect that is what happened to me.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="CPU Temperature Comparison" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CPU_Compare_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590990225" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>To create HDE Files the ARRIRAW Files need to be compressed, this compression is done by the CPU. If your CPU is throttling itself because it's too hot, it won't be able to perform at max speed, thus the HDE Compression is slower. That is why we see slower read and write speeds when the computer is hot, the HDE is being compressed slower so there isn't as great of a need for data in and data out.</p>
<p>Sometimes we were travelling in cars doing data on the run on a hot day in Outback South Australia, if I didn’t have the car fully sealed, the laptop out of the sun and the air-con on full my offload speeds would plummet. Thermal throttling at it’s finest. Even when working in air conditioned offices, the CPU demand would be so high for sustained periods of time that the MacBook Pro couldn’t dissipate heat fast enough, hence the 900MB/s -&gt; 780MB/s handicap detailed above. Based on this evidence and my experience using HDE on a MacBook Pro since, I conclude that thermals play a massive role when using HDE on-set.</p>
<p>My best advise is to always do HDE Offloads in an air-conditioned space. Where this isn’t possible, make sure you are in a cool place, in the shade with adequate airflow. Of course this issue is only prevalent when using a <a href="https://www.apple.com/au/macbook-pro-16/" target="_blank" title="MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">MacBook Pro</a>, other systems like the <a href="https://www.apple.com/au/mac-pro/" target="_blank" title="Mac Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mac Pro</a> and <a href="https://www.apple.com/au/imac-pro/" target="_blank" title="iMac Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">iMac Pro</a> have much better heat dissipation and this thermal throttling will likely never become an issue for you.</p>
<p>If you aren’t using SSD RAIDs (900MB/s), your offloads will be capped out by the speed of the Regular SATA SSDs (500MB/s) or Regular SATA HDDs (130MB/s). When your speeds are capped by your destination drives the CPU doesn’t need to work as hard to process the HDE, thus the CPU only works at 40% rather than 90% and generates less heat meaning the thermal throttling problem won’t effect you.</p>
<p>To illustrate this, below is a screen grab from I a job I did in March 2020. We were using Regular SATA SSDs (500MB/s). Given that the computer can only write HDE Files to the SATA SSDs at a max of 500MB/s the CPU Speed needed to process the HDE is much less. You can see the CPU performing at around 40% and the CPU Temp is only at 73°C. This is vastly differently to the previous example using SSD RAIDs (900MB/s) where the CPU was performing at 90% and the CPU Temp was at 97°C.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="SATA SSD Speed with HDE" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SATA_SSD_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590991363" style="float: none;"></p>
<p><strong>CPU Load</strong></p>
<p>There is one more thing to keep in mind when it comes to CPU and HDE. As previously explained, excessive heat will thermally throttle your CPU and thus your CPU’s performance. What else causes poor CPU Performance? Having a poor CPU! I’ve found that the 6-Core and 8-Core CPUs that are present in the 2018 and 2019 15"/16" MacBook Pros are adequate to keep up with Top-End HDE Offloading. Once you start dipping down to 4-Core CPUs in older computer’s I suspect the CPU Processing won’t be able to keep up with the speed of the Codex Mags or the SSD RAIDs making the computer the weak link in the chain. Please keep this in mind when assessing if your computer will be adequate for a HDE ARRIRAW Job.</p>
<p><strong>ProRes HDE?</strong></p>
<p>When shooting on an Alexa Mini or Alexa Mini LF you basically have two recording options, ProRes and ARRIRAW.</p>
<p>When you shoot ARRIRAW you can choose to enable HDE via Codex Device Manager. When HDE is enabled the mag will mount as ‘A013_hde’, when HDE is disabled the mag will mount as ‘A013’.</p>
<p>This toggle exists all of the time, so if you leave HDE Enabled in Codex Device Manager and insert a mag that contains ProRes Footage, it will show up as both 'A013' and ‘A013_hde’. Given it's a ProRes Card, the '_hde' indicates a ProRes HDE Format which actually doesn’t exist. Thus <span>‘A001_hde’</span> actually can not exist because there is no such thing as ProRes HDE. The actual footage displayed to the user is the same as you can see below, but the naming conventions are bound to cause some confusion.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="ProRes HDE" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ProRes_HDE_1024x1024.jpg?v=1590992001" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>I’m sure Codex will fix this in a future software update but in the mean time the best practice is be keenly aware of the format you are shooting. I’ve had jobs that bounce between ProRes and ARRIRAW and I was offloading the ARRIRAW as HDE. For circumstances like this I would know if a mag was ProRes or ARRIRAW. When it was ARRIRAW I would explicitly enable HDE via Codex Device Manager, when it was ProRes I would explicitly disable HDE via Codex Device Manager.</p>
<p>The toggle is accessed by selecting Codex Device Manager from your menu bar on macOS and clicking Preferences. From there you can checkbox HDE on or off. I always do this when no card is mounted to the computer.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="HDE Toggle" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/HDE_Toggle_grande.jpg?v=1590975396" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>It’s certainly annoying to manually toggle this option on a per card basis but in my eyes it’s better than getting confused and accidentally offloading a ProRes Mag with '_hde' file naming which suggests some form of Non-Existent HDE.</p>
<p><strong>Codex Only for CFast</strong></p>
<p>This last quirk is by far the most frustrating. Let me tell you how I discovered it. I was on a Car Job, we were alternating between Alexa Mini and Alexa Mini LF. The Alexa Mini was fitted on a tracking vehicle, it was shooting 3.4K ARRRIAW which I was processing via HDE. One morning they came back from the first run and had filled five 256GB CFast Cards. We had 7 Cards with the camera package, this meant until I offloaded and checked a card we only had two more cards to use with that camera, one of which was half full and still in the camera. The 1st AC had tried to get them to drop the cards to me sooner so I could start turning them around but they didn’t want to make the pitstop.</p>
<p>As soon as they returned to base I started offloading the smallest card based on info provided by the 1st AC. I was doing a HDE Offload using the <a href="https://codex.online/?action=asset&amp;id=DCB66A8F-22BA-4AE8-B997-FD5A846ABEEF" target="_blank" title="Codex CFast 2.0 Reader PDF Manual" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex CFast 2.0 Card Reader</a>. This was Day 4 of a 4 Day Job and up until that point the Codex Reader was fine, however on this morning something wasn’t quite right. The HDE Offload finished way quicker than expected and flagged an error. Given the time pressure I was under I didn’t have time to troubleshoot properly, I assumed it was an issue with the card reader and swapped in my <a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/1186725-REG/lexar_lrwcr1tbna_pro_workflow_cr1_cfast.html" target="_blank" title="Lexar CFast 2.0 Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lexar CFast 2.0 Reader</a>. To my surprise I wasn’t able to do a HDE Offload with this reader. To get things done quickly I just did a regular ARRIRAW Offload, I checked and cleared the card and sent it back out with the tracking vehicle. We had SSDs on hand which essentially saved us in this instance.</p>
<p>They were happy enough with the amount of cards they now had to get through what they needed to shoot, the pressure was off a little to get the remaining four 256 CFast Cards offloaded so I had a moment to properly troubleshoot. It seemed the issue with the Codex CFast 2.0 Card Reader was the USB Cable, I swapped it out and things worked fine for my CFast HDE Offloads. What bugged me is that I couldn’t use HDE with a Third Party CFast Reader, I tried many different cards with my Lexar Reader and each time I couldn’t get the HDE Partition to mount via Codex Device Manager.</p>
<p>A few weeks later I was helping a friend troubleshoot some HDE Issues via phone, they were shooting ARRIRAW on an Alexa Mini with CFast Cards. They wanted to use HDE but the rental house had only provided a <a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/1032304-REG/sandisk_sddr_299_a46_extreme_pro_cfast_reader_writer.html" target="_blank" title="SanDisk CFast 2.0 Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">SanDisk CFast 2.0 Reader</a> with the kit. When they enabled HDE on the ARRIRAW CFast Cards, no dice, the partition wouldn’t mount. I flagged with them that I suspected they needed an actual Codex CFast Reader to use HDE which they enquired about to the rental house. In response the rental house then sent out an <a href="https://www.angelbird.com/prod/cfast-20-card-reader-2204/" target="_blank" title="Angelbird CFast 2.0 Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">Angelbird CFast 2.0 Reader</a> which uses USB-C. <a href="https://www.angelbird.com/journal/news/arri-and-angelbird-introduce-cfast-20-card-94/" target="_blank" title="ARRI and Angelbird CFast Endorsement" rel="noopener noreferrer">ARRI has endorsed Angelbird CFast 2.0 Cards</a> as being suitable for the Alexa Mini so the hope was that a card reader from the same brand would work for HDE. Again, no luck. They could only access regular ARRIRAW files, not the ARRIRAW HDE Files.</p>
<p>This confirmed it for me. Codex Device Manager will only allow HDE ARRIRAW on an Alexa Mini when you use the official Codex CFast 2.0 Card Reader.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Codex CFast HDE Tick" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Codex_CFast_Tick_grande.jpg?v=1590993019" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>In one way it does make sense, the software is called ‘Codex Device Manager’, it manages Codex Devices. Lexar, SanDisk and Angelbird Products aren’t Codex Devices, thus Codex Device Manager doesn’t manage them which means HDE doesn’t work.</p>
<p>However, I find it quite disappointing. We live in a more transparent and open source world today than we did five years ago. To block a software feature because a user is utilising cheaper hardware doesn’t seem fair. Especially as third party card readers live in DIT or Data Wranglers Kits all the time, often as a spare because the Codex CFast 2.0 Card Reader can be cost prohibitive to them.</p>
<p>With that being said, it’s unclear if the HDE block is software or hardware based. Given the Codex CFast 2.0 Card Reader came out with the Alexa Mini in 2015 and HDE wasn’t released till 2019, it’s hard to believe that there would have been enough foresight to know that in four years time we’ll have developed an ARRIRAW Compression Feature (HDE) and that we’ll need a hardware component in the Codex CFast 2.0 Card Reader to ensure users can only use this future feature with Codex Hardware. It’s much more likely that the limitation is put in place via software. Codex Device Manager detects the CFast Reader, if it’s a Codex Reader HDE is given the green light, if it’s a Third Party Reader then HDE is blocked.</p>
<p>Of course this won’t effect you when using an Alexa SXT, Alexa LF or Alexa Mini LF as these all use a property Codex Mag and Codex Mag Reader, no third party options exist so you won’t have a problem. It’s just something that you should be aware of when using an Alexa Mini, CFast Cards and ARRIRAW.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>CONCLUSION</strong></span></h1>
<p>I trust that this post has proven helpful to you, especially if you haven’t been hands on with HDE before. Please learn from my issues so that you can come onto set well equipped with knowledge that will assist you in dealing with HDE Problems swiftly and without stress.</p>
<p>If you have any questions or queries, please let us know in the comments section below!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/how-do-i-playback-prores-mxf-files-from-the-alexa-mini-lf</id>
    <published>2019-11-11T14:11:00+11:00</published>
    <updated>2020-05-22T13:57:03+10:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/how-do-i-playback-prores-mxf-files-from-the-alexa-mini-lf"/>
    <title>HOW DO I PLAYBACK PRORES MXF FILES FROM THE ALEXA MINI LF?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Bradley Andrew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span style="color: #000000;">When working with any form of camera footage that uses Apple's ProRes Codec, it's always been easy. Traditionally they have been .mov files, you can play them back as simply as pressing the spacebar and using <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-au/guide/mac-help/mh14119/mac" target="_blank" title="Quick Look" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quick Look on macOS</a>. If you are using the Alexa Mini LF on-set and shooting ProRes, the first thing you'll notice is that the footage is no longer .mov files, they are .mxf files. <br></span> <br><span style="color: #000000;">On my first Mini LF job I couldn't playback using Quick Look or QuickTime depite the footage being ProRes. I ended up using <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">DaVinci Resolve</a> and things went fine. But surely we don't want to lose the ability to quickly preview a file with Quick Look? Thankfully we don't have to, allow me to show you how.</span>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">THE SOLUTION<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">A simple software update is all that is required. You need to install the <a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/DL2020?locale=en_US" target="_blank" title="Pro Video Formats Software Update" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pro Video Formats 2.1.1 Update</a> provided by Apple. Stated in the version history of this update is the precise thing we need to solve our problem:</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The Pro Video Formats package also includes the following MXF support:</span><br><span style="color: #000000;">    •    Play MXF files in QuickTime Player and other supported macOS applications</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Pro Video Formats" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ProVideoFormats_medium.png?v=1573435996" style="float: none;"></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Apple also has a little bit more information about MXF Files if you'd like some further reading: <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT204322" target="_blank" title="About Pro Video Formats and MXF Files" rel="noopener noreferrer">About Pro Video Formats and MXF Files</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Download the update, install the update and restart your computer. You should then be good to go.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">But wait, there is a little complication...</span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">THE COMPLICATION<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The <a href="https://www.arri.com/en/learn-help/learn-help-camera-system/tools/arriraw-converter" target="_blank" title="ARRIRAW Converter" rel="noopener noreferrer">ARRIRAW Converter Software (ARC) by ARRI</a> seems to conflict with the code related to Apple's Pro Video Formats. You likely already have ARC installed as it's been a good tool to have in the kit for playing back ARRIRAW Files. The only solution that I currently know of is to uninstall ARRIRAW Converter. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Before you make the decision to ditch ARC, consider how much you use the software and read my outline below which details how ProRes .mxf files will appear in macOS pending what you have installed.<br></span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">Old Version of Pro Video Formats | Current Version of ARRIRAW Converter</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">When you try to play back ProRes .mxf Files in Quick Look:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Quick Look 01" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/QuickView_01_grande.jpg?v=1573438142" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">When you try to play back ProRes .mxf Files in QuickTime Player:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/QuickTime_01_grande.jpg?v=1573438092" alt="QuickTime 01"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">As you can see above, no luck with Quick Look and QuickTime Player can't open the files, it just displays an error message.</span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">New Version of Pro Video Formats | Current Version of ARRIRAW Converter</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">When you try to play back ProRes .mxf Files in Quick Look:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Quick Look 02" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/QuickView_02_grande.jpg?v=1573438095" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">When you try to play back ProRes .mxf Files in QuickTime Player:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="color: #000000; text-decoration: underline;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/QuickTime_02_grande.jpg?v=1573438090" alt="QuickTime 02"></span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">As you can see above, the Pro Video Formats has fixed the playback in QuickTime as promised. But when it comes to Quick Look, it still doesn't work. This is the conflict between ARRIRAW Converter and Pro Video Formats in action.<br></span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">New Version of Pro Video Formats | Uninstalled ARRIRAW Converter</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">When you try to play back ProRes .mxf Files in Quick Look:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Quick Look 03" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/QuickView_03_grande.jpg?v=1573438095" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">When you try to play back ProRes .mxf Files in QuickTime Player:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/QuickTime_02_grande.jpg?v=1573438090" alt="QuickTime 03"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">As you can see above, everything is working. This confirms the conflict that occurs when you have ARRIRAW Converter installed.<br></span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">What Did I Do?<br></span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I decided to uninstall ARRIRAW Converter. In the past I had found a few instances where ARC could play back ARRIRAW a touch smoother than DaVinci Resolve, but the times where I had used it were far and few between. I use Quick Look all the time. Being able to preview ProRes Files with a simple tap of the spacebar is super valuable to me so that's the way I went. Let's hope ARRI sorts out this clash sometime soon so we can have the best of both worlds!<br></span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">OTHER INFORMATION<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">FILE ASSOCIATION</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">You may need to change the file association of .mxf files within macOS. You can do this by selecting a .mxf file, Right Click -&gt; Get Info or Command + I, then select the software you'd like to use in the 'Open With' Section. I changed it to QuickTime.<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Get Info Settings" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/GetInfoSettings_grande.jpg?v=1573438832" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>ALTERNATE SOFTWARE<br></strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Before implementing this fix I was able to use other applications to open the ProRes .mxf files, these were <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">DaVinci Resolve</a>, <a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/premiere.html" target="_blank" title="Premiere Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Premiere Pro</a> and <a href="https://www.videolan.org/vlc/index.html" target="_blank" title="VLC Player" rel="noopener noreferrer">VLC Player</a>. Please keep these in mind should you run into any issues.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Another piece of software that I have not tested but has recently come to my attention is <a href="https://videovillage.co/screen/" target="_blank" title="Screen" rel="noopener noreferrer">Screen</a>, a video player specifically designed for film work. Seems like a great tool to have in the toolkit.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Screen App" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Screen_medium.png?v=1573441006" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SOFTWARE VERSIONS<br></strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">What I have described above occurred on my 2018 15" MacBook Pro running macOS Mojave 10.14.6. I was running ARRIRAW Converter 4.1 BETA. Should the software get updated in the coming months this will give you something to compare to.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">As always, if you have any questions, thoughts or feedback, let us know in the comments below!</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Thanks!</span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">UPDATE (19/02/20)<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The clash between ARRIRAW Converter (ARC) and Apple's QuickLook has been fixed with a software update. Christian from ARRI reached out and informed me of a new version of ARC which addresses this issue. Thanks Christian! The updated ARC Software is Version 4.2.4 compared to Version 4.1 BETA that I was using when I initially wrote this post.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">ARRIs official release notes state:</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>'The QuickLook plugin for MXF/ProRes files has been fixed. (mac OS, ARC 4.2.4)'</strong><br>and<br><strong>'QuickLook plugin bug fixes (there was a conflict when Apples Pro Video-Format was installed in parallel)'</strong><br><br>I am still running a 2018 15" MacBook Pro running macOS Mojave 10.14.6 but I have now updated to ARRIRAW Converter 4.2.4 and the issue has been resolved on my system. I can utilise ARC and still use QuickLook to view ProRes .mxf Files.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">My current advise is for all users to re-install ARC, just make sure it's the newest version and you select the correct build for your operating system. There are separate versions for 10.14 (Mojave) and 10.15 (Catalina). ARRIs official download link can be found here: </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong><a href="https://www.arri.com/en/learn-help/learn-help-camera-system/tools/arriraw-converter" target="_blank" title="ARC Official Download" rel="noopener noreferrer">ARRIRAW CONVERTER OFFICIAL DOWNLOAD LINK</a></strong><br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Thanks!</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/what-is-the-fastest-offload-software</id>
    <published>2019-10-07T17:53:00+11:00</published>
    <updated>2019-10-10T13:50:17+11:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/what-is-the-fastest-offload-software"/>
    <title>WHAT IS THE FASTEST OFFLOAD SOFTWARE?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Bradley Andrew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #000000;">If you are performing data management on set you are likely using <a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silverstack</a>, <a href="https://hedge.video/" target="_blank" title="Hedge" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hedge</a>, <a href="https://www.imagineproducts.com/product/shotput-pro" target="_blank" title="Shotput Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Shotput Pro</a> or <a href="https://yoyotta.com/" target="_blank" title="YoYotta" rel="noopener noreferrer">YoYotta</a>. Here at Film Drives we are always striving for faster offloads so we decided to put them to the test. The results were surprising, so allow us to walk you through the process, the results and the implications as we discover which offload software is the fastest.<br></span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">HYPOTHESIS<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">A few years ago I did a TVC all around Australia using the <a href="https://arrirentalgroup.com/alexa65/" target="_blank" title="Alexa 65" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alexa 65</a>. It was one of the first jobs in the country to use this new camera system and there was a lot of prep work and learning to be done as we figured out the best way to manage bucket loads of data while traveling from state to state on a very tight schedule.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Before the job I had been a dedicated <a href="https://www.imagineproducts.com/product/shotput-pro" target="_blank" title="Shotput Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Shotput Pro</a> user. I believe this was before <a href="https://hedge.video" target="_blank" title="Hedge" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hedge</a> was on the scene and I wasn't aware of <a href="https://yoyotta.com/" target="_blank" title="YoYotta" rel="noopener noreferrer">YoYotta</a>. I had been curious about <a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silverstack</a> for a while but had never given it a red hot go. If there was any job worthy of testing out a different data management system, it was this one.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">We were using the Codex Vault XL coupled with a MacBook Pro and 2x 5 Bay RAID 5 Drives. Standalone I was getting around 600MB/s off the RAID Drives. I recall offloading with Shotput Pro and thinking it wasn't as fast as it should be. So I decided to grab a trial version of Silverstack XT and run some tests. The specifics I have archived in my email but I believe we were getting around 100MB/s faster offloads with Silverstack compared to Shotput Pro. This was using the exact same drive, media and connection configuration. When you are doing 1TB Offloads this 100MB/s equates to a massive time saving. For the rest of the job I used Silverstack and it has been my software of choice ever since.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Over the past few weeks I've been testing out our new Data Deluxe System and as always, speed is a priority. I want to be able to recommend the fastest and safest offload tool so I decided to run an experiment and pit the four big players against one another. This was my process.</span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">EXPERIMENT<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SOLID STATE DRIVES</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The SSDs that I used for the tests were <a href="https://www.samsung.com/us/computing/memory-storage/solid-state-drives/ssd-860-evo-2-5--sata-iii-4tb-mz-76e4t0b-am/" target="_blank" title="Samsung SSDs" rel="noopener noreferrer">Samsung 4TB 860 EVO 2.5" SATA SSDs</a>. These SSDs average around <span style="text-decoration: underline;">492MB/s WRITE SPEED</span> and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">528MB/s READ SPEED</span>. The SATA Form Factor has adequate heat dissipation due to it's larger size and allows for consistent offload speeds during lengthy transfers as no thermal throttling takes place. Each SSD was formatted as Mac OS Extended (Journaled) with a GUID Partition Map.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Data Deluxe Destination SSDs" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/DD_DestinationsSSDs_grande.jpg?v=1569983512" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>DESTINATION DRIVES</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The Data Deluxe is capable of mounting 4x 2.5" SATA SSDs simultaneously. There are two SSD Readers in the system that connect via USB 3.1 Gen 2 which gives you 10GB/s (1250MB/s) connection speeds per reader. Each SSD Reader can mount 2x SSDs, thus the 4x SSDs in total between the two units. If you max out 2x SSDs as described above they will come in at <span style="text-decoration: underline;">984MB/s WRITE SPEED</span> and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">1056MB/s READ SPEED</span> which is under the 1250MB/s provided by USB 3.1 Gen 2 which means there is no bottleneck present with the connection interface.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Data Deluxe Destination SSD USB-C Connection" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/DD_SSDPorts_grande.jpg?v=1569983512" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SOURCE MEDIA</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I don't readily have access to an <a href="https://www.arri.com/en/camera-systems/cameras/alexa-lf" target="_blank" title="Alexa LF" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alexa LF</a> or <a href="https://www.arri.com/en/camera-systems/cameras/alexa-mini-lf" target="_blank" title="Alexa Mini LF" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alexa Mini LF</a> alongside their corresponding Media and Card Readers. So I gathered some Alexa LF Footage from <a href="https://www.thevisionhouse.com.au/" target="_blank" title="The Vision House" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Vision House</a> and stored it on a <a href="https://filmdrives.com/products/custom-ssd" title="Film Drives Custom SSD">Custom Film Drives SSD</a> which runs in our USB 3.1 Gen 2 Enclosure. <br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Alexa LF" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/AlexaLF_grande.jpg?v=1569983514" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">For the purposes of this test, this External SSD will be acting as our source media for the offloads. The files for offload were made up of four clips shot on the Alexa LF in 4.5K Open Gate ARRIRAW, we didn't use <a href="https://codex.online/codex-hde" target="_blank" title="Codex HDE" rel="noopener noreferrer">HDE</a> thus the files are a .ARI Image Sequence. In total, the card came in at 212GB.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Data Deluxe Media SSD" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/DD_MediaSSD_grande.jpg?v=1569983510" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>COMPUTER</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">For the tests I connected the Data Deluxe SSDs and the External Film Drives Custom SSD to my 2018 15" MacBook Pro that is equipped with an AMD Raedon Pro 560X GPU, 32GB of RAM and 1TB Internal SSD. It was also connected to a <a href="https://www.amd.com/en/products/graphics/radeon-rx-vega-64" target="_blank" title="Vega 64" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vega 64</a> eGPU via Data Deluxe. The MacBook Pro is running the latest version of macOS Mojave 10.14.6.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SOFTWARE</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">To level out the playing field I decided to download the latest trial versions of all the offload software and clean install them on my system. The version numbers were as follows:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Shotput Pro Icon" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Shotput_small.png?v=1569986998" style="float: none;"></span><span style="color: #000000;"><br>Shotput Pro 2019.2.17<br><br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"></span> <img alt="Silverstack Icon" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Silverstack_06d1c0d7-1692-4df5-b44b-b308807659b0_small.png?v=1569987001" style="float: none;"><span style="color: #000000;"></span><span style="color: #000000;"><br>Silverstack XT 6.5.7</span></p>
<div style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"></span></div>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Hedge Icon" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Hedge_small.png?v=1569987003" style="float: none;"></span><span style="color: #000000;"><br>Hedge 19.4<br><br></span>
</div>
<div style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"></span></div>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="YoYotta Icon" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/YoYotta_0c6253af-ed1e-4853-9047-d7cd2044cb1b_small.png?v=1569986998" style="float: none;"></span><span style="color: #000000;"><br>YoYotta 3.0</span>
</div>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>PROCEDURE</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Before each offload test I would format and delete any existing files off the Destination SSDs, this means they would be fresh 4TB SSDs as if you were starting a brand new job. To ensure each Destination SSD was performing as it should a speed test was run using Blackmagic Disk Speed Test. This allowed me to get a metric for the write speed and read speed of each SSD prior to the offload, this number stayed consistent throughout each software eliminating drive performance as a variable.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I would also run a speed test on the 'Source Media' SSD before each offload test to ensure that the write speed and read speed was consistent. Again, eliminating drive performance for the source media as a variable.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">For this test I decided to offload the source media to 3x Destination SSDs as 3 Copies of your footage is generally considered the gold standard. I wanted the test to be as close to a real world, on-set situation as possible.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Prior to each test I went through and checked all the offload settings of each software to ensure things like Source Integrity Verification were on and that they were using the XXHash Checksum. Source Integrity Verification adds an extra layer of reliability to your offload as it scans your source media to check for errors in the data. XXHash is my preferred checksum method as it's the fastest and has proven very reliable, it's also the best checksum method for an ARRIRAW Image Sequence as there are thousands of files to run checksums on.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">During the offload process I would record the screen of my MacBook Pro using <a href="http://www.telestream.net/screenflow/overview.htm" target="_blank" title="ScreenFlow" rel="noopener noreferrer">ScreenFlow</a>. I set <a href="http://www.telestream.net/screenflow/overview.htm" target="_blank" title="ScreenFlow" rel="noopener noreferrer">ScreenFlow</a> to run at 25fps for each recording as this is the standard frame rate here in Australia.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">When the offload was finished I would end the screen recording and analyse what had been recorded. This allowed me to dial in frame by frame exactly when the offload started and exactly when the offload finished. From this information I could get an objective measure of the time it took to complete the transfer and verification. This means I wasn't reliant on the time readout from each software which would have introduced a bias as there wouldn't be a consistent measure of time.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">While I was at it, I checked the software's estimated time remaining at the start of the offload and compared it to the final offload time. I figured this was a great time to also compare the estimation engine of each application as historically I have found them to be a bit inaccurate.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Some software does the offload and verification process in tandem, dynamically switching between offloading the footage and verifying the copy. Other software does all the offloading as a batch followed by all of the verification as a batch. Where applicable I have broken down the offload time, verification time and total time as separate pieces of data for you to consider.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I believe that outlines all of the measures and variables I had in place. Now for what you've really be waiting for...the results!</span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">SHOTPUT PRO OBSERVATIONS</span><br></strong></h1>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong><img alt="Shotput Pro" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Shotput_01_grande.png?v=1569984015" style="float: none;"></strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I ran Shotput Pro in it's classic 'Preset View'. Job Sequence was set to it's default value 'Optimize Drive Use' which I have found to be the best choice based on past experience. I used the XXHash-64 Checksum. I only enabled Text Reports as I've had instances in the past where the PDF Report Option will try and get a frame grab for every single frame in an image sequence which is very time consuming. Ignore Hidden Files and Folders is a great default so I left that as is. I had 'Source Integrity Verification' turned on.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Please find the screen grabs of my settings below:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Shotput Settings 01" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ShotputSettings_01_grande.png?v=1569983997" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Shotput Settings 02" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ShotputSettings_02_grande.png?v=1569984000" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Shotput Settings 03" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ShotputSettings_03_grande.png?v=1569983998" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">These are the pre-offload speed test results of the Destination SSDs and Media SSD:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Shotput Pro Pre-Offload Speed Test" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ShotputPro_SpeedTest_grande.png?v=1569972140" style="float: none;"></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SHOTPUT PRO RESULTS</strong><br>Estimated Time: 33:00 Minutes</span><br><span style="color: #000000;">Offload Time: 17:01 Minutes</span><br><span style="color: #000000;">Verification Time: 13:30 Minutes</span><br><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Total Time: 30:31 Minutes</span></span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SILVERSTACK OBSERVATIONS</strong></span></h1>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong><img alt="Silverstack" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Silverstack_grande.png?v=1569985405" style="float: none;"></strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">For this test I was running Silverstack XT. In the Preferences -&gt; Copy &amp; Jobs Tab I left Number of Parallel Tasks set to it's default '1 (Optimized, Recommended)'. Number of Parallel Jobs set to '1'. Read Buffer Size set to '8MB (Recommended)'.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Silverstack Setting 01" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SilverstackSettings_01_grande.png?v=1569984485" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">In the Offload Clips Window I set Verification Behaviour to 'Verify All Destinations, Include Source Verification (included in Copy Job)' which is the setting that I mainly use when offloading with Silverstack. This setting does the offload and verification process in tandem, dynamically switching between offloading the footage and verifying the copy, thus Offload Time and Verification Time can't be calculated. I used the XXHash64 BE Checksum.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Silverstack Setting 02" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SilverstackSettings_02_grande.png?v=1569984485" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">These are the pre-offload speed test results of the Destination SSDs and Media SSD:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Silverstack Pro Pre-Offload Speed Test" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Silverstack_SpeedTest_grande.png?v=1569972141" style="float: none;"></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SILVERSTACK RESULTS</strong><br>Estimated Time: 25:30 Minutes</span><br><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Total Time: 26:11 Minutes<br></span></span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>HEDGE OBSERVATIONS</strong></span></h1>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong><img alt="Hedge" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Hedge_01_grande.png?v=1569984685" style="float: none;"></strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Hedge loves to simply things. The preferences weren't as complex as Shotput Pro or Silverstack. As you can see below, in Preferences -&gt; Transfers I could enable 'Detect Source Read Errors' and 'Create Transfers Logs and MHLs'. That's about it, both of which I enabled.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Hedge Settings" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Hedge_02_grande.png?v=1569987666" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I couldn't even select what checksum to use. But upon investigating the Text Log that is generated upon completion of an offload, I can confirm that Hedge uses XXHash64 BE Checksums.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Hedge Reports" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/HedgeLog_grande.png?v=1569984900" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Hedge does the offload and verification process in tandem, dynamically switching between offloading the footage and verifying the copy, thus Offload Time and Verification Time can't be calculated.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">These are the pre-offload speed test results of the Destination SSDs and Media SSD:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Hedge Pre-Offload Speed Test" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Hedge_SpeedTest_grande.png?v=1569972139" style="float: none;"></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>HEDGE RESULTS</strong><br>Estimated Time: 22:00 Minutes</span><br><span style="text-decoration: underline; color: #000000;">Total Time: 22:16 Minutes<br></span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>YOYOTTA OBSERVATIONS</strong></span></h1>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong><img alt="YoYotta" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/YoYotta_grande.png?v=1569985264" style="float: none;"></strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I'd never used YoYotta before so it took a little bit of getting used to in regards to finding where the settings were and figuring out exactly what they did.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">In Preferences I selected 'Extract Metadata', Silverstack does this as a standard so I figured it would put it on par with the processing that Silverstack does. I left 'Split Image Sequences' at it's default of 10,000 frames, this was likely to play a role given we are testing an ARRIRAW Image Sequence. I enabled 'Source Verify' so that it matched the source verification that all the other software uses.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="YoYotta Settings 01" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/YoYottaSettings_01_grande.png?v=1569985265" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I seems that YoYotta does an XXHash and MD5 Checksum as default. This is useful as some older LTO Systems require the use of the slower MD5 Checksums. How they implement this with an image sequence and still keep it fast is unclear. What would make sense to me is to run an XXHash Checksum on each individual frame and an MD5 Checksum on each folder that houses an image sequence.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="YoYotta Settings 02" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/YoYottaSettings_02_grande.png?v=1569985255" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">These are the pre-offload speed test results of the Destination SSDs and Media SSD:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="YoYotta Pro Pre-Offload Speed Test" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/YoYotta_SpeedTest_grande.png?v=1569972142" style="float: none;"></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>YOYOTTA RESULTS</strong><br>Estimated Time: 25:00 Minutes</span><br><span style="color: #000000;">Offload Time: 13:13 Minutes</span><br><span style="color: #000000;">Verification Time: 12:33 Minutes</span><br><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Total Time: 25:46 Minutes<br></span></span></p>
<br>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">ANALYSIS<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>TOTAL TIME</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">To help understand things visually I have put together this graph. It details the 'Total Time' of each offload side by side, these are the results:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Software Comparison Graph" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SoftwareComparison_Graph_1024x1024.png?v=1569973215" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">As I stated before, the results were quite surprising. I expected there to be differences but I didn't expect there to be such a great time difference between each software. In particular the difference between Shotput Pro and Hedge was over 8 Minutes, this is a lot of time, especially when you are finishing the final offload for the day.<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">Even the 3.5 Minute to 4 Minute Difference between Hedge and YoYotta / Silverstack is considerable. Just looking as these figures it seems that the fastest offload software is Hedge.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">I wasn't quite satisfied just yet. I wondered is Source Verification played that much of a difference in offload time and since Hedge only specified their Source Verification as 'Detect Source Read Errors' it was unclear if it was indeed performing the same Source Verification as other software and thus giving it an unfair advantage. So I decided to run the same test through each software with Source Verification turned off. The toggle for Source Verification in Shotput Pro, Silverstack and YoYotta can be seen below highlighted in yellow:<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">Shotput Pro</span></strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Shotput Pro Source Verification" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ShotputSourceVerify_grande.png?v=1569986171" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">Silverstack</span></strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Silverstack Source Verification" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SilverstackSourceVerify_grande.png?v=1569986104" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">YoYotta</span></strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="YoYotta Source Verification" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/YoYottaSourceVerify_grande.png?v=1569986121" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">These were my results:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Source Verification Comparison Graph" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SourceVerification_Graph_1024x1024.png?v=1569976362" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">The tests showed that with source verification turned off, Shotput Pro performed 59 Seconds faster, Silverstack performed 17 Seconds faster and YoYotta performed 4 Seconds faster. I didn't try Hedge with 'Detect Source Read Errors' off as this was more a test to see if the other software could catch up to Hedge with it disabled. I would say that the difference is mostly negligible (4 Secs / 17 Secs) except in the case of Shotput Pro where the difference was almost a minute. Faster, but still quite far off from any other software in terms of 'Total Time' for a complete offload. This test made it quite clear that even if Hedge isn't doing a source verification that is on par with the other software, it still is faster. Even when the others have source verification turned off. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">ESTIMATED TIME</span></strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">I noted the 'Estimated Time' displayed at the start of an offload, I then compared this to the 'Total Time' to see how accurate the software algorithms were that inform the user of time till completion. Below is the graph:<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Estimate Comparison Graph" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Estimate_Graph_1024x1024.png?v=1569978992" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">To help quantify the accuracy I performed an equation, Estimated Time <span class="ILfuVd NA6bn"><span class="e24Kjd">÷</span></span> Total Time, accurate to two decimal places. This gives me a percentage of the deviation between estimate and result. Each software ranks as follows:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Shotput Pro:</span> Within 8% Accuracy<br><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Silverstack:</span> Within 3% Accuracy<br><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Hedge:</span> Within 1% Accuracy<br><span style="text-decoration: underline;">YoYotta:</span> Within 3% Accuracy</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">I would consider 5% an acceptable tolerance between estimate and result. Hedge, Silverstack and YoYotta all fell within this window, with Shotput Pro falling short.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">Due to the nature of TVC Work in Australia I am often working on set as a 2nd AC and DIT simultaneously. I generally have a good sense of how long an offload will take, but the software readout is very useful as well. If I need to be present on set and my data station is just off set, I generally set a timer on my Apple Watch, then when it buzzes I will leave set to check the offload and finalise the reports. If I am solely relying on the software readout for setting my Apple Watch timer, an inaccurate readout can result in a few minutes where the offload is complete but I don't know it's finished yet. Not a deal breaker, but on those data heavy jobs it can make a real difference by saving you many minutes throughout the day. I like to say 'if your computer isn't working and you have footage to offload, you're likely doing something wrong'.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">Props go to Hedge on this front for their very impressive estimation algorithm with only a 1% deviation in accuracy.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>OFFLOAD TIME AND VERIFY TIME<br></strong></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">In Silverstack, rather than running the offload and verification process in tandem, you can alter this setting in the Offload Clips Window which allows Silverstack to function in the traditional manner of offload first, verify second.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Silverstack Alt Settings" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SilverstackSettings_04_grande.png?v=1569986105" style="float: none;"></span></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">As a further look into exactly what was happening I decided to breakdown the offload and verify process between the different software, except for Hedge as this wasn't an option. For this comparison Source Verification was on.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">Here is the data:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Offload Verify Data" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/OffloadVerify_Data_grande.png?v=1569976697" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">Here is the graph:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Offload Verify Comparison Graph" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/OffloadVerify_Graph_1024x1024.png?v=1569976698" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">Looking at this data, the verification processes of Silverstack and YoYotta perform very much the same, while YoYotta trumps Silverstack ever so slightly in regards to offload speed. Worth noting, YoYotta performs XXHash and MD5 Checksums while Silverstack performs just XXHash Checksums, given that the YoYotta verification time is only 7 Seconds longer than Silverstack this is to be commended.<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;">The stark contrast comes when comparing Silverstack / YoYotta to Shotput Pro, the verification time is slower by 1 Minute but the offload time falls behind by around 3.5 Minutes. Considering the gold standard status that Shotput Pro holds in the industry, it seems like there is definitely room for improvement and a bit of catch up needs to be done in order to match the offload speeds of their competitors.<br></span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">FOLLOW UP OBSERVATIONS<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I wanted to present a fair, unbiased and well rounded set of data to the reader. Part of that process was checking that I didn't make any mistakes. I decided to touch base with the software developers, Pomfort (Silverstack), Imagine (Shotput Pro), Hedge and YoYotta to listen to what they had to say.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">One point that was noted is that my tests did a great job at comparing each software in an identical environment, but they didn't factor in how each software was verifying the data or exactly what was going on behind the scenes. This tied back to one of the opening paragraphs in this article, it isn't just about speed, it's also about safety and reliability. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">After a few emails back and forth it became clear that I should run my tests again while analyzing the data from Activity Monitor or <a href="https://bjango.com/mac/istatmenus/" target="_blank" title="iStat Menus" rel="noopener noreferrer">iStat Menus</a>. When you open Activity Monitor on macOS you can select the 'Disk' Tab and see the amount of data that is being written and read by each application and process. So that is exactly what I did.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The images presented below are screen grabs from Activity Monitor before the offload starts and immediately after it has finished. For all offloads I had Source Verification enabled.<br></span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">SHOTPUT PRO</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">At the end of a complete offload, Shotput Pro had Written 591.89GB and Read 975.54GB.<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Shotput Pro Extra Tests" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Shotput_ExtraTests_1024x1024.png?v=1570405899" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">SILVERSTACK</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Silverstack works a little bit differently than other software. There is the core Silverstack App which the user interfaces with, then they have a utility app that does the actual offloading called 'pfndispatchcopy'.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">It seemed that my offload was broken down into four distinct sequences when I analysed the screen recording. What immediately made sense was that Silverstack offloads and verifies a single clip, then moves onto the next clip. This is how Silverstack can have an interruption to an offload (ie. accidentally ejected drive, loss of power, etc.) and still pick up where it left off in terms of the offload. This became evident when I compared my clip sizes to the Bytes Written and Bytes Read in Activity Monitor.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">For reference my clip sizes were as follows:<br>C001 - 34.03GB (34,027,024,648 bytes)<br>C002 - 31.82GB (31,812,593,114 bytes)<br>C003 - 114.35GB (114,320,183,778 bytes)<br>C004 - 31.84GB (31,833,481,218 bytes)</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Below you can see the screen grab before the offload had begun, followed by the screen grabs taken at the end of each 'pfndispatchcopy' operation, one per clip. When added together, at the end of a complete offload Silverstack had Written 592.18GB and Read 974.02GB.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Before</strong><br><img alt="Silverstack Extra Tests 01" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Silverstack_ExtraTests_01_1024x1024.png?v=1570405892" style="float: none;"><br><strong><br>Offloads 1 and 2</strong><br><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Silverstack_ExtraTests_02_1024x1024.png?v=1570405890" alt="Silverstack Extra Tests 02"><br><br><strong>Offloads 3 and 4</strong><br><img alt="Silverstack Extra Tests 03" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Silverstack_ExtraTests_03_1024x1024.png?v=1570405901" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">HEDGE</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">At the end of a complete offload, Hedge had Written 592.12GB and Read 394.94GB. I should clarify that this is at the <span style="text-decoration: underline;">end</span> of the offload, meaning when Hedge displays the transfer as complete via both UI and system notification.<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Hedge Extra Tests" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Hedge_ExtraTests_1024x1024.png?v=1570408313" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">If you were to leave Hedge after it has displayed 'Disk is Done - Transfers are Completed' you will notice that it continues to read from the destination drives. After 12 Minutes 4 Seconds it seemed to stop reading from my destination drives and came in with 592.14GB Bytes Written and 966.03GB Bytes Read.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Hedge Extra Tests 02" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Hedge_ExtraTests_02_1024x1024.png?v=1570409965" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">YOYOTTA</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">At the end of a complete offload, YoYotta had Written 592.35GB and Read 788.82GB.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="YoYotta Extra Tests" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/YoYotta_ExtraTests_1024x1024.png?v=1570405900" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">FOLLOW UP ANALYSIS<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">So you might be thinking, how the heck am I meant to interpret all of this? I must admit, it's complex. Allow me to break it down.<br></span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">GB  vs. GiB</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">My first question came from looking at the 'Bytes Written' metric. All of the applications seemed to present a similar readout:</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Bytes Written</strong><br>Shotput Pro - 591.89GB<br>Silverstack - 592.18GB<br>Hedge - 592.12GB<br>YoYotta - 592.35GB</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">This averages to 592.14GB. In total I was offloading 212.04GB to 3 Destinations, so it made sense that this number should be 636.12GB running with the equation 212.04 x 3. So why was there a 44GB difference? Surely all 4 Applications weren't copying an incorrect amount of data. They in fact were not.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Activity Monitor uses binary sizing. 1GB = 1024 x 1024 x 1024. Referenced as GiBs.<br>Disk Files use decimal sizing. 1GB = 1000 x 1000 x 1000. Referenced as GBs.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">For our purposes it is easier to discuss GBs. In order to convert the Activity Monitor GiBs to GBs you need to perform this calculation. 'Number' x 1024 x 1024 x 1024. In this instance, that equation is 592.14 x 1024 x 1024 x 1024 = 635,805,483,663 Bytes. Very close to our expected 636GB. Thank you to the teams at Pomfort and YoYotta for clarifying this difference and providing the equation.</span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">RESULTS</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">With that equation in mind, I have converted all of the data above into GBs and presented it below, broken down for each application.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Activity Monitor Data (GBs)" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ExtraTests_GB_Data_1024x1024.png?v=1570412811" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">We have already determined that the Data Written is on par with what is expected and that each application wrote a similar amount of data which can be interpreted as correct. Getting a gauge on the Data Read takes a little bit more explanation.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Traditionally speaking, there are four steps in the offload and verify process. With three tasks that need to be completed after an offload to ensure that it has been copied successfully. They are as follows:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Data Copying<br></strong>Data is copied from the Source to the Destinations. A checksum hash is generated for the Source.<strong></strong></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong><img alt="Checksum Explanation 01" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ChecksumExplanation_01_grande.png?v=1570417194" style="float: none;"></strong></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Destination Verify</strong><br>Read the data from each destination and create a checksum hash for each destination.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Checksum Explanation 02" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ChecksumExplanation_02_grande.png?v=1570417196" style="float: none;"><br><strong></strong></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Source Verify</strong><br>Read the source again and create a checksum hash for the second time. The first checksum is generated on the initial read which happens when the copy is underway. This whole process is referred to above as Source Verification.<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Checksum Explanation 03" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ChecksumExplanation_03_grande.png?v=1570417067" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Compare</strong><br>Compare all checksum hashes against the ones that were generated during the copy process.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Checksum Explanation 04" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ChecksumExplanation_04_grande.png?v=1570417077" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">So how does this apply to the Data Read in our tests? When you are copying from the source to three destinations the data will be read once from the source. When you do a Destination Verify the data will be read once from each destination, in our example three times. When you do a Source Verify the data will be read again from the source. In our example you would expect as follows:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><img alt="Expected Reads" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ExpectedReads_grande.png?v=1570417277" style="float: none;"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Looking at the data that we have gathered above, we can run a simple equation to determine how many reads are happening, thus giving us an indication of what is likely occurring with each software. The calculation that I used is Actual Data Read (GB) <span class="ILfuVd NA6bn"><span class="e24Kjd">÷</span></span> Source Media (GB). <br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Shotput Pro</strong> returned a value of <span style="text-decoration: underline;">4.94 Reads</span> (1047.48 <span class="ILfuVd NA6bn"><span class="e24Kjd">÷</span></span> 212.04). It makes sense to round this number up to 5 Reads. This indicates that Shotput Pro is likely performing all 5 Reads that we would expect.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Silverstack</strong> returned a value of <span style="text-decoration: underline;">4.93 Reads</span> (1045.85 <span class="ILfuVd NA6bn"><span class="e24Kjd">÷</span></span> 212.04). It makes sense to round this number up to 5 Reads. This indicates that Silverstack is likely performing all 5 Reads that we would expect.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Hedge</strong> returned a value of <span style="text-decoration: underline;">2.00 Reads</span> (424.06 <span class="ILfuVd NA6bn"><span class="e24Kjd">÷</span></span> 212.04). This indicates that Hedge is likely performing only 2 Reads, we can only assume one read is for the initial copy and one read for the source verify.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">As mentioned above, when I left Hedge open and running it continued to read from my destination drives for 12:04 Mins after the completion of the copy. When it stopped reading it came in at 966.03 GB Read. If we equate that, <strong>Hedge</strong> returned a value of <span style="text-decoration: underline;">4.56 Reads</span> (966.03 <span class="ILfuVd NA6bn"><span class="e24Kjd">÷</span></span> 212.04). This is closer to the 5 Reads that we would expect.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>YoYotta</strong> returned a value of <span style="text-decoration: underline;">3.99</span> (826.99 <span class="ILfuVd NA6bn"><span class="e24Kjd">÷</span></span> 212.04). It makes sense to round this number up to 4 Reads. This indicates that YoYotta may not be performing a Source Verify Read due to the result of 4 Reads compared to the 5 Reads that is expected. The team at YoYotta assure me that source verification is indeed happening so I <span data-dobid="hdw">theorise</span> the software is likely combining it's copy read and it's source verify read as well as doing individual reads to each of the three destination drives.<br></span></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;">INTERPRETATION</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">It seems that Shotput Pro and Silverstack are essentially performing the same copy and verify operation coming in with 5 Reads. It's worth noting that Silverstack performs this operation faster, perhaps it is better optimised for dealing with SSDs.</span></p>
<span style="color: #000000;">YoYotta seems to be performing a similar yet slightly different copy and verify operation with 4 Reads in total. My assumption is that it combines the 'copy read' and 'source verify read' into one process. Also worth noting is that YoYotta does XXHash Checksums and MD5 Checksums in tandem, a stark difference from all other software which is always one or the other.</span><br><br><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Update:</strong></span><br><span style="color: #000000;">I have received an update from the team at YoYotta as to why I wasn't seeing the Source Verify (5th Read) on my tests.</span><br><br><span style="color: #000000;"><span color="#333333"><span style="font-family: .SF NS Text;">'YoYotta will perform a Source Verify (Second Read and Checksum) of source footage when it sees new footage on a particular drive. </span></span><span color="#333333"><span style="font-family: .SF NS Text;">When YoYotta sees clips previously processed on the same drive it realises that they have already been verified twice. </span></span><span color="#333333"><span style="font-family: .SF NS Text;"><span color="#333333">So for real-world camera card offloads, YoYotta will always perform the second source verification pass.'<br><br>As I processed the tests numerous times with the same set of drives, the source verify was bypassed by YoYotta, the first run when I wasn't looking at the Activity Monitor Data would have completed the full 5 Reads. For new camera cards YoYotta will perform the full 5 Reads, putting it on par with the Silverstack and Shotput Pro. I can force YoYotta to forget my drives via terminal and run the test again to be sure, I will endeavor to do this when I have a moment.</span></span></span></span><br><span color="#333333" style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: .SF NS Text;"><span color="#333333"></span></span></span><br><span style="color: #000000;">While Hedge seems to be performing a completely different copy and verify operation to any of the other applications. Based on the information detailed above, it appears that Hedge does a 'copy read' and a 'source verify read' as part of it's copy and verify operation. This is then followed by a background operation that goes on to perform a 'destination read' on each destination. </span>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Based on information gathered from Hedge's website and various sources online, it seems that Hedge does more than an XXHash Checksum to verify the data that has been copied correctly. This includes 'cross verifying issue reporting provisions provided by macOS' and 'smart detection of kernal errors during write operations'.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Putting this all together while utilising the Hedge lingo, it appears like Hedge does an initial copy and verify, this verify uses their integrated software called 'Fast Lane'. From what I can gather 'Fast Lane' is a combination of source verification (if you have it selected) and other software checks based on macOS provisions. Then Hedge goes on to use another integrated software called '<a href="https://hedge.video/checkpoint" target="_blank" title="Hedge 'Checkpoint'" rel="noopener noreferrer">Checkpoint</a>' which then performs a 'destination read' on every offload destination and creates checksum hashes.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">There seems to be some controversy about Hedge's copy and verify process online. This is mainly because it is very different to the traditional method that everyone is used to.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The primary concern is that macOS has a feature often referenced as 'System Caching' which happens on an individual drive level as well as an operating system level. 'System Caching' keeps recently used files and stores them in the Computer's RAM. In normal operation this is great as it allows the system to show the user files from the RAM rather than the drive which is always faster. This comes down to the read/write speed of RAM being quicker than the drives that store data.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">In most cases, when you complete a copy operation the system is moving data from your Source Media, through the Computer's RAM and then onto the Destination Drives. Many people feel that for a true verification to be done, the data needs to be read from the destination drives, not the RAM, as the RAM is temporary and a completely separate instance to the data that you are handing off when you eject the destination drive from the system.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">This primary concern stems from an assumption that the claimed 'macOS Provisions' utilised by Hedge are simply checksum hashes generated from the data stored in the Computer's RAM. You can check out this <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/editors/comments/6zs3y4/lets_talk_dit_software_hardware_workflows/" target="_blank" title="Reddit Post" rel="noopener noreferrer">Reddit Post</a> to read more on this topic.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The secondary concern is that when Hedge gives you the big tick of approval saying that your offload is complete, you can then eject the destination drive and hand it off to the client with no consequences. What this means is that Hedge has run it's 'Fast Lane' software on your offload, it has generated reports complete with XXHash Checksums and said that your data is backed up and safe. As mentioned above, once 'Fast Lane' has been completed, Hedge then runs '<a href="https://hedge.video/checkpoint" target="_blank" title="Hedge 'Checkpoint'" rel="noopener noreferrer">Checkpoint</a>' which is essentially 'destination reads'. When you eject your destination drives this '<a href="https://hedge.video/checkpoint" target="_blank" title="Hedge 'Checkpoint'" rel="noopener noreferrer">Checkpoint</a>' process is stopped, meaning you don't have completed 'destination reads'. In the eyes of many technicians, this isn't a good thing as it means your offload safety is being determined by only the 'System Caching' detailed above and the other checks run by Hedge.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">How I would best think about it is two completely different types of verification:</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Traditional Verification</strong><br>After the copy process, the software reads again from the source and all destination drives, it creates seperate checksum hashes and compares them to the ones generated during the copy process. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>New School Verification</strong><br><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 01</span><br>During the copy process, the software is utilising 'macOS Provisions' to detect offload errors while running checksums on the source. Multiple facets of propriety code also continuously run to ensure data integrity.<br><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 02</span><br>Once Part 01 is complete, the software reads from all the destination drives in the background. It creates seperate checksum hashes and compares them to the ones generated during Part 01. This process is considered optional and can be cancelled at anytime by closing the software or ejecting the destination drive.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Shotput Pro, Silverstack and YoYotta all use <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Traditional Verification</span> while Hedge uses <span style="text-decoration: underline;">New School Verification</span>. </span><span style="color: #000000;">The important thing to keep in mind, when you see a Completion Tick in Shotput Pro it means something vastly different to the Completion Tick you see in Hedge. Many people assume the tick means the same thing, it doesn't, as detailed by the evidence above.</span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">CONCLUSION<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">This has been a very informative process for me. It's really helped to clarify how each software performs and what considerations need to be made when comparing each software side by side.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Initially I was looking at the data related to speed only and had concluded that Hedge performed the fastest when it came to the offload and verification. But looking at the results from my follow up it became clear that this was an inaccurate assessment. Hedge was completing a New School Verification, while all other applications were using the Traditional Verification Method. The two couldn't be compared as the processes utilised are vastly different. It'd be like comparing apples to oranges.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">How would this be thought about if you ignored the 'macOS Provisions' and other proprietary code run by Hedge? For Hedge's verification process to be on par with all of the others (based on the Activity Monitor data) you'd need to wait an additional 12:04 Mins for it's 'destination reads' to be complete via '<a href="https://hedge.video/checkpoint" target="_blank" title="Hedge 'Checkpoint'" rel="noopener noreferrer">Checkpoint</a>'. This takes Hedge's total copy and verify time up to 34:20 Mins, previously coming in at 22:16 Mins. This is slower than Shotput Pro, Silverstack and YoYotta. With that being said, it's not a fair comparison as Hedge does utilise 'macOS Provisions' and runs proprietary code, conforming to <span style="text-decoration: underline;">and</span> inventing the 'New School Verification' Method.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">What is conclusive, is that Shotput Pro, Silverstack and YoYotta all use a very similar copy and verification method, with Silverstack and YoYotta coming in faster than Shotput Pro. Silverstack clocking in at 26:11 Mins, YoYotta at 25:46 Mins and Shotput Pro at 30:31 Mins.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">So where does this leave us?</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">It doesn't feel right to declare a clear winner. If you take this as an apples to apples comparison as it was originally intended to be, it's clear that Hedge is the fastest. But keep in mind that what you get with Hedge is different to what you get with Shotput Pro, Silverstack or YoYotta.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">If the utilisation of the tried and true Traditional Verification Method is important to you, then use Silverstack, YoYotta or Shotput Pro with the above speed comparisons in mind.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">If you have read the Follow Up Section above, have a solid understanding of what it means and feel good about the New School Verification Method that Hedge uses, then use Hedge.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>OTHER POINTS WORTH NOTING</strong></span></p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #000000;">These speed differences are apparent with SSDs, when using spinning disk drives that run between 100MB/s and 250MB/s the speed difference is likely to be less obvious.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #000000;">It's likely that each application has different copy engines built into them. This means that if you are offloading ARRIRAW, the software may use a different process than if it was offloading RED and a different process again if it was offloading ProRes in .mov format. Each different file format may use a different process and thus generate different results. This article is a great example of ARRRIRAW and SSDs, so if you are dealing with something different, keep this is mind and do your own tests.<br></span></li>
<li><span style="color: #000000;">I tweaked the 'Job Sequence' Setting in Shotput Pro from the default 'Optimize Drive Use' to 'All at Once'. 'All at Once' achieved a Total Time of 30:41 Mins, compared to the 30:31 Mins of 'Optimize Drive Use'. This test was intended to see if one setting performed better over the other when dealing with SSDs.<br></span></li>
<li><span style="color: #000000;">Slightly faster 'Total Time' Offloads can be achieved with Silverstack when you choose offload first, verify second rather than the default of offload and verify in tandem. Silverstack completed the transfer in 26:11 Mins 'Total Time' when used in tandem. Silverstack completed the transfer in 25:55 Mins 'Total Time' when used as offload then verify. Both were measured with Source Verification Enabled.<br></span></li>
</ul>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">KEEP US HONEST<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I believe in being transparent and up front about what you are doing or trying to do. If there is anything I can do that allows you to check up on my process, I will. So please help to keep us honest and check through the evidence below. I have uploaded the screen recordings of each software's offload. They are long, boring videos but you can scrub through and see the offloads happen in real time. A good way to verify the times listed above are actually what happened.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">If you would like to download the Excel File that was used to log the original data, that is <a href="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Offload_Software_Tests.xlsx?2788" target="_blank" title="Download Original Excel Data" rel="noopener noreferrer">available for download here</a>.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">If you would like to download the Excel File that was used to log the follow up data, that is <a href="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Activity_Monitor_Analysis.xlsx?2815" target="_blank" title="Download Follow Up Excel Data" rel="noopener noreferrer">available for download here</a>.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SHOTPUT PRO</strong></span></p>
<p><strong><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9Ddk5LrsIxM?VQ=HD720%E2%80%9D%20frameborder=" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" width="“1280”" height="“720”"></iframe></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Please Note: Upon Offload Completion, Shotput Pro states 'Time Elapsed' to be 30:16, but we have noted it as 30:31. This is because Shotput Pro doesn't include the generation of Reports / MHLs in this 'Time Elapsed' number. All of the the software was clocked off after this paper trail was generated, we treated Shotput Pro in the same manner.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SILVERSTACK</strong></span></p>
<p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/M893UtcD4IE?VQ=HD720%E2%80%9D%20frameborder=" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" width="“1280”" height="“720”"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>HEDGE</strong></span></p>
<p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XOvY2caa0yU?VQ=HD720%E2%80%9D%20frameborder=" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" width="“1280”" height="“720”"></iframe> </p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>YOYOTTA</strong></span></p>
<p> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/a9EZhmpjeO8?VQ=HD720%E2%80%9D%20frameborder=" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" width="“1280”" height="“720”"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SILVERSTACK FOLLOW UP<br></strong></span></p>
<p><strong><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zhoQUbLGovE?VQ=HD720%E2%80%9D%20frameborder=" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" width="“1280”" height="“720”"></iframe></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">This is a video of the follow up test we ran with Silverstack. You can see how Silverstack branches off from the main application and uses 'pfndispatchcopy' to process each offload and verification clip by clip.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>HEDGE FOLLOW UP<br></strong></span></p>
<p><strong><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UMxJUGfYBq8?VQ=HD720%E2%80%9D%20frameborder=" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" width="“1280”" height="“720”"></iframe></strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">This is a video of the follow up test we ran with Hedge. You can see how Hedge keeps running read operations to the destination drives after it has notifed the user that the offload is complete and verified. This can be seen in both Activity Monitor and iStat Menus.<br></span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">CLOSING COMMENTS<br></span></strong></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I hope this has helped shed some light on what the fastest offload software is. As always, we're open to constructive feedback, questions and comments. Please let us know below!</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Thanks!</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/on-set-with-the-alexa-mini-lf-first-impressions</id>
    <published>2019-08-26T13:17:00+10:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-14T19:20:05+11:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/on-set-with-the-alexa-mini-lf-first-impressions"/>
    <title>ON-SET WITH THE ALEXA MINI LF | FIRST IMPRESSIONS</title>
    <author>
      <name>Bradley Andrew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Last week I had my first job with the <a href="https://www.arri.com/en/camera-systems/cameras/alexa-mini-lf" target="_blank" title="Alexa Mini LF" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alexa Mini LF</a>. It was great to get hands on with ARRI's latest camera and test out some of the new hardware. I thought I'd put together this post for those that are curious about the new <a href="https://codex.online/products/media/compact-drive" target="_blank" title="Compact Drives" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex Compact Drives</a> and their companion <a href="https://codex.online/products/media-stations/compact-drive-reader" target="_blank" title="Compact Drive Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">Compact Drive Reader</a> as well as some of the ins and outs of the workflow.<br>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">CODEX COMPACT DRIVES<br></span></strong></h1>
<p>Our camera kit came with 4x Codex Compact Drives and 1x Codex Compact Drive Reader which was provided by Panavision Melbourne.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong></strong><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Codex_01_large.jpg?v=1566781069" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Each Compact Drive is 1TB, which gives you 960GB of usable space. Initially I was under the impression that these Compact Drives were setup much like the previous generations of Codex Drives, in a RAID 0 Configuration. I was pondering if they were made up from 4x 256GB SSDs or 2x 512GB SSDs RAIDed together. But Oliver from ARRI has cleared up the confusion. Please see the update below.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>UPDATE:</strong><br>Oliver from ARRI has clarified that the Codex Compact Drives <span style="text-decoration: underline;">do not</span> use a RAID Configuration like the previous generation. He says 'Codex uses a customized (wider) M.2 SSD with a higher number of memory chips for parallel writing. So you might call it some sort of RAID on a chip'. Thank you for the clarifcation Oliver!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Below you can see the connection that the Compact Drive uses to interface with the Alexa Mini LF and the Compact Drive Reader.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Codex_07_large.jpg?v=1566781724" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Below you can see the back of a Codex Compact Drive. It contains information such as Model Number, Serial Number, etc.</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Codex_03_large.jpg?v=1566781722" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>I was particularly surprised at how small the Compact Drives are. They truly are compact. Measuring in at 44mm x 77mm x 9.8mm, they fit snugly in the palm of your hand as depicted below.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Codex_02_large.jpg?v=1566781727" alt=""></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The Compact Drives come in a protective, plastic case. Our 2nd AC kept saying it's like a cigarette case from an 80s Film.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Codex_05_large.jpg?v=1566781728" alt=""></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The case is made from plastic with high density foam on the inside. As shown above the Compact Drive fits within the case perfectly. Below you can see the foam cut out, it has very tight tolerances. If you plan on leaving camera tape on your mag and closing the case, it's not going to happen. The camera tape adds thickness and the case won't click closed properly.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Codex_06_large.jpg?v=1566781727" alt=""></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">To be honest I would have expected something a little more durable. Below is an image of the release which allows the case to open. When transporting a fresh mag on the job this case slipped from my hand and fell onto soft grass, the very minor fall ejected the lock mechanism and the Compact Drive came tumbling out of it's case. Not very ideal. It would work to prevent a small impact, but too bad if it was a large impact. What if it was raining, the mag may survive the fall but if the case pops open there is a hot chance of it making contact with the environmental elements such as water, dirt, etc.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Codex_04_large.jpg?v=1566781723" alt=""><strong></strong></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">CODEX COMPACT DRIVE READER<br></span></strong></h1>
<p>Panavision supplied our Compact Drive Reader with a Belkin Thunderbolt 3 to Thunderbolt 3 Cable. This worked no problems but definitely wasn't required as the Compact Drive Reader functions on USB-C, not Thunderbolt. A difference to keep in mind when thinking about offload speeds and different cables.</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CodexReader_01_large.jpg?v=1566782975" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>I ran all offloads from my 2018 6-Core MacBook Pro. This laptop is equipped with 4x TB3 / USB 3.1 Ports that run at full bandwidth. Using the TB3 Cable provided by Panavision, my MacBook interpreted the device correctly as USB-C and ran at USB 3.1 Gen 2 Bandwidth (10GB/s or 1250MB/s). It is fully powered via bus power and doesn't require any external power to function correctly.</p>
<p>Many Data Wranglers in Melbourne are still running the older style MacBook Pro which comes equipped with 2x TB2 Ports and 2x USB3.0 Ports. I was curious if the Compact Drive Reader would function on this setup so I tested it.</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CodexReader_02_large.jpg?v=1566782976" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>The answer was yes. In the image above you can see the Compact Drive Reader connected to an older style MacBook Pro with a USB-C to USB-A Cable. While still fully powered via bus power you won't have full data bandwidth when running in this configuration. The Compact Drive Reader will be limited by USB3.0 (5GB/s or 420MB/s), this means your read speeds will be significantly lower than using the exact same Compact Drive and Reader on a newer style USB-C MacBook Pro. If you are offloading to SSDs this is going to impact your offload times, if using 5400rpm spinning disk drives then you won't see any speed difference between an older MacBook Pro and a newer MacBook Pro.</p>
<p>One interesting point worth noting, there seems to be a fan somewhere in the Compact Drive Reader. When I was offloading footage I'd notice a fan come on from time to time. It's very distinct, you'll definitely hear it in a normal indoor environment. I suspect this is to help regulate the temperature of the Compact Drive so that it doesn't overheat.</p>
<p>Initially I thought the Compact Drive may have had the fan which in some regards would make sense as it could cool itself both in-camera and in-reader, but there are no air vents on the Compact Drive so I suspect it's housing just acts as a heatsink. The Compact Drive Reader has what looks like a vent on the rear end. While I couldn't see a fan, I could definitely hear one, so I expect this may serve as air intake or exhaust.</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CodexReader_03_large.jpg?v=1566784251" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">WORKFLOW<br></span></strong></h1>
<p>On this particular job we were shooting 4.5K Open Gate (4448 x 3096) in ProRes 444 XQ. I actually would have liked to be shooting ARRIRAW on this one so I could have given Codex HDE a solid test run, but that wasn't the format of choice.</p>
<h3><strong>.MXF FILE WRAPPER</strong></h3>
<p>The most important thing to keep in mind when shooting ProRes on Alexa Mini LF is that it wraps ProRes in a .mxf wrapper as opposed to the .mov wrapper that you would be used to when working with a regular Alexa Mini. As you can see below, you have the .mxf ProRes Clips and the standard ARRI Metadata presented on the card.</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CodexWorkflow_01_large.jpg?v=1566784791" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>Normally I would use Apple Quick Look or Quicktime Player to watch through the ProRes .mov Clips for quality control, when wrapped in .mxf neither of these worked. I ended up using <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">DaVinci Resolve</a> to playback the clips. I tested a few other software packages for their compatibility with the files, <a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/premiere.html" target="_blank" title="Premiere Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Premiere Pro</a> worked, <a href="https://www.arri.com/en/learn-help/learn-help-camera-system/tools/arriraw-converter" target="_blank" title="ARRIRAW Converter" rel="noopener noreferrer">ARRIRAW Converter</a> worked, <a href="https://www.videolan.org/index.html" target="_blank" title="VLC" rel="noopener noreferrer">VLC</a> worked.</p>
<p><strong>UPDATE:</strong><br>You can playback ProRes in a .mxf Wrapper in both Quick Look and QuickTime, you just need to tweak some software. Read more about it on <a href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/how-do-i-playback-prores-mxf-files-from-the-alexa-mini-lf" target="_blank" title="How to Playback ProRes MXF Files" rel="noopener noreferrer">this blog post</a>.</p>
<h3><strong>SOFTWARE</strong></h3>
<p>In terms of software, you should make sure you have the newest version of <a href="https://codex.online/products/device-manager" target="_blank" title="Codex Device Manager" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex Device Manager</a>. Recently they released V5 which is in BETA and provides compatibility for the Alexa Mini LF and <a href="https://codex.online/codex-hde" target="_blank" title="HDE" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex HDE</a>.</p>
<p>For this job I used <a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pomfort Silverstack</a>. I did a few tests with an older version of Silverstack and a few tests with the latest version of Silverstack. As you can see in the images below, the old version of Silverstack didn't work too well with the Alexa Mini LF Footage. The clip names had a frame count added to the end, the thumbnails didn't work, the metadata didn't carry across, etc. This is because the old version of Silverstack doesn't know about the Alexa Mini LF and it's .mxf ProRes Format, thus it imports the clips as 'Generic Clips' without any of the bells and whistles that you would expect.</p>
<p><strong>OLD VERSION OF SILVERSTACK</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CodexWorkflow_04_2048x2048.jpg?v=1566786277" style="float: none; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p><strong>LATEST VERSION OF SILVERSTACK</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CodexWorkflow_05_2048x2048.jpg?v=1566786278" style="float: none; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>To amend this, run the latest version of Silverstack. As you can see above, thumbnails work, metadata has carried across and the filenames are presented as they should be. No matter which data management software you use, <a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silverstack</a>, <a href="https://hedge.video/" target="_blank" title="Hedge" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hedge</a> or <a href="https://www.imagineproducts.com/product/shotput-pro" target="_blank" title="Shotput Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Shotput Pro</a>, make sure you are on the latest version.</p>
<h3><strong>FORMATTING MAGS<br></strong></h3>
<p>As part of my normal workflow, when I have backed up a mag and signed it all off I will format the mag before returning it to set. This means that when it is inserted into a camera, particularly an ARRI Camera, it will prompt you to format the mag prior to use. This is great as it leaves no room for error, if a card prompts you for a format when you do a reload you are doing the right thing, if you get no prompt perhaps something is wrong and requires a second look.</p>
<p>The Alexa Mini LF fits into this workflow as you would expect. In Disk Utility you can see the 960GB Compact Drive which is formatted as UDF by the camera.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CodexWorkflow_02_grande.jpg?v=1566786268" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; float: none;"></p>
<p>If you format it as MS-DOS (FAT) in Disk Utility, when inserted into the camera with the EVF open it will prompt you to format the mag, just like the regular Alexa Mini. Winning.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CodexWorkflow_03_grande.jpg?v=1566786271" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; float: none;"></p>
<h3 style="text-align: left;"><strong>DATA RATE<br></strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: left;">One last note on workflow that will essentially make or break your job. Be aware of your shooting data rate and make sure you have fast enough drives. The Alexa Mini LF is very data hungry.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We were shooting 4.5K Open Gate (4448 x 3096) in ProRes 444 XQ which allows for 46 Minutes Shooting Time at 25fps for 1TB of Data. This essentially means that for every 5 Mins you shoot, you have 128GB of data to offload.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">If you tackle this with 5400rpm spinning disk drives that 128GB will take around 40 Mins to offload. That means 5 Mins Shooting = 40 Mins Offloading, that's an 8:1 Ratio in terms of offload time to shooting time. You will very quickly get backlogged and wind up with a bunch of data overtime at the end of the day.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">For the Alexa Mini LF you really need to be offloading to SSDs or 5 Bay RAIDs that have a write speed of at least 420MB/s. If you don't you're asking for trouble.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We shot some stuff at 33.333fps and 40fps at 4.5K Open Gate, this racks up the data super quick. We did a few short takes and I had 300GB to offload within a matter of minutes.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">To some it may seem counter intuitive to spend more money on drives but I assure you that the more you spend on faster drives (SSDs or Big RAIDs), the more you will save on labour, particularly in the form of overtime at the end of the day. Plan ahead and be prepared.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">CONCLUSION<br></span></strong></h1>
<p>This was my first job with the Alexa Mini LF, it went smoothly with minimal fuss. There will be many more things to play with and test out going forward but I hope this helps to give a few of you a heads up when you get sent out with this camera for the first time.</p>
<p>Thanks!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/will-thunderbolt-make-my-drives-faster</id>
    <published>2019-02-19T10:23:00+11:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-19T10:23:31+11:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/will-thunderbolt-make-my-drives-faster"/>
    <title>WILL THUNDERBOLT MAKE MY DRIVES FASTER?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Bradley Andrew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[In short, sometimes. But in most circumstances it won't make a difference. <br> <br>This is a common assumption that comes up time and time again. I have had many Production Managers assure me that 'I got Thunderbolt Drives so they'll be the fastest and we'll be covered'. This is almost never true and I would like to explain why. Dive deep into the wonderful world of hard drive speeds.<br> <br>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">WHAT IMPACTS THE SPEED?<br></span></strong></h1>
Many parts and components make up a hard drive that you buy off the shelf. Each and every one of these parts plays a role in the end performance that you will experience as a user. I summarize them as the 4 Pillars of Hard Drive Performance: <strong>Drive, Enclosure, Connection Interface, Cable / Computer Interface</strong><br> <br><strong>DRIVE</strong><br>The physical drive that lives inside your hard drive is the key player when it comes to speed. Most commonly you would know this as Hard Disk Drive (HDD) or Solid State Drive (SSD).<br><br>HDDs are made up from multiple magnetic platters that physically spin inside the drive. Your data is stored on these magnetic platters and a read/write arm moves across them to record your data and to recall your data when it is required. These are the most affordable drives, yet due to their mechanical nature they have poorer performance when it comes to speed.<br><br>
<div style="text-align: center;"><img alt="HDD" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/HDD_large.jpg?v=1549850908" style="float: none;"></div>
<br>SSDs are made from flash storage chips that are housed on a Printed Circuit Board (PCB). There are no moving parts, all of the legwork is done by the copper connections and the circuits. These drives are more expensive but also offer the best performance.<br><br>
<div style="text-align: center;"><img alt="SSD" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SSD_large.jpg?v=1549850909" style="float: none;"></div>
<br><strong>ENCLOSURE</strong><br>In any consumer hard drive product you will find a HDD or SSD inside of a wonderful housing, this housing is known as the enclosure. The enclosure is what you typically think of when you imagine a hard drive. Some enclosures are made of plastic, others are made of aluminum. This material choice plays a small role in heat dissipation but is largely about durability, aesthetics and price.<br><img alt="HDD Enclosures" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ENCLOSURE_BOTH_1024x1024.jpg?v=1549851422" style="float: none;"><br>What we are really concerned about is speed. What part of the enclosure impacts speed? It's the PCB or circuit board. The PCB inside of an enclosure essentially acts as an intermediary between the drive and the computer. Think of it as the knife that bridges the gap between the force of your cutting hand and a piece of food. Or the tennis racquet that transfers the strength of your arm to the force of a moving tennis ball. In the same way a sharper knife or a lighter racquet gives you better results, an effective enclosure will provide you with absolute speed.<br><br>The two main players on the circuit board are the SATA Connection and the Connection Interface. We will cover Connection Interface below as it's incredibly important and worthy of it's own pillar, but the SATA Connection should not be overlooked. Below is an image if a bare bones HDD, the connector on the bottom is what a SATA Connection looks like:<br>
<div style="text-align: center;"><img alt="SATA Connection" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SATA_large.jpg?v=1549851963" style="float: none;"></div>
In terms of speed, the current standard is SATA Revision 3.2 which boasts a speed throughput of 1900MB/s. Prior to that, SATA Revision 3.0 (which is the most common SATA Connection you will see in external hard drives) ran at 600MB/s. Dating back to the Mid-2000s was SATA Revision 2.0 which performed at a modest 300MB/s.<br><br>
<div style="text-align: center;"><img alt="SATA Revision Speed Graph" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SATA_Graph_grande.png?v=1549852466" style="float: none;"></div>
<br>While all of these numbers may come across as confusing, the one thing that you need to know is that a newer revision of SATA means faster speeds. This isn't a common cause of a slow hard drive but it does crop up from time to time and is worthy of your time and consideration.<br><br>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<p><strong>CONNECTION INTERFACE</strong><br>You will typically know of connection interfaces as USB3, USB3.1, Thunderbolt 2, Thunderbolt 3, Firewire 800, eSATA, etc. I would define these as external connection interfaces, while the SATA Revisions that we just discussed are considered internal connection interfaces.<br><br>Each one of these connection interfaces runs at a different speed, some faster than others. You'll see terms being thrown around like '40Gbps' or 'SuperSpeed+', these can be confusing and quite often misleading. We all understand the concept of a Megabyte and most people have a good gauge of how a Megabyte makes up a Gigabyte and a Gigabyte makes up a Terabyte, it's metric and works on the concept of 1000 (1000 Megabytes is a Gigabyte and 1000 Gigabytes are a Terabyte). I believe it's easier to understand when we use terms that we are used to. So let's break it down in Megabytes Per Second (MB/s).</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img alt="Connection Interface Graph" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Connection_Interface_Speeds_-_Small_2048x2048.jpg?v=1549855598" style="float: none;"><br><br>As you can see, there is a wide array of speed difference between different connections which will have an impact on the performance of your hard drive. It's very clear that USB3.0 is slower than Thunderbolt 2, but this difference in speed won't always mean your hard drive will perform slower which we explore below in 'The Weak Link of the Chain'.</p>
<p><strong>CABLE / COMPUTER INTERFACE</strong><br>So you have a USB3.0 Port on your hard drive, great, but what if you are using a USB2.0 Cable? Or if your computer is an old 17" MacBook Pro that has USB2.0 Ports on the side? Will that impact your speed, yes.<br><br>In conjunction with all of the above elements we need to consider the role of the cable and the computer's connection interfaces. This is the last major bridge that your data needs to cross. Today we live in a world with Cable Adapters, USB Hubs and what some would call a wild west of cables coming out of China. <br><br>Knowing your computer is simple. The connection interfaces will be in line with the ones that we described above and their speeds the same. You can easily look up your computer specs or a product listing and this information will be accessible.<br><br>Cables are a bit trickier. Many have different connectors on each end and the gauge of cable that is between these two connectors can be of varying quality. The cable quality and cable connectors will impact the speed. It's very easy to fall down the rabbit hole when it comes to cables and adapters, this will be explored in a different blog post. For now, you just need to be aware that they play a role in your hard drives performance.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">THE WEAK LINK IN THE CHAIN<br></span></strong></h1>
<p style="text-align: left;">This is by far the most important concept to understand when it comes to hard drive speed. You know that old saying 'a chain is only as strong as it's weakest link'? The same principle is in effect here. <strong>Your hard drive is only as fast as the slowest component in use.</strong> In every single hard drive, one of the four pillars (drive, enclosure, connection interface, cable / computer interface) will be the weakest link in the chain and cause a limitation in overall speed. The best way to explore this is by example:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><br><strong>Example 01: (Slow Cable)</strong><br><img alt="Example 01" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CHAIN_EXAMPLE_01_1024x1024.jpg?v=1549867133" style="float: none;"><br>Here we see the USB2.0 Cable becoming the weak link in the chain. Despite all of the other upstream components being faster we default to the speed of USB2.0 due to that one cable at the end of our connection.<br><br><strong>Example 02: (Slow HDD)</strong><br><img alt="Example 02" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CHAIN_EXAMPLE_02_1024x1024.jpg?v=1549867134" style="float: none;"><br>This is a very common limitation, the HDD will be the weak link in the chain. Everything else is offering great speeds but the HDD is stuck at 115MB/s, it's the slowest component and thus will become the max speed we can attain.<br><br><strong>Example 03: (Slow Connection and Cable)</strong><br><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CHAIN_EXAMPLE_03_1024x1024.jpg?v=1549867133" alt="Example 03"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">When using an SSD, your drive speed surpasses the speed of the common USB3.0 Interface. In this instance you will only be able to use your SSD at 420MB/s despite it being capable of running at 520MB/s. This is because the USB3.0 Port, Cable and Connection is the weak link in the chain.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><br><strong>Example 04: (Slow SSD)</strong><br><img alt="Example 04" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CHAIN_EXAMPLE_04_1024x1024.jpg?v=1550530386" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">When using high end connections like USB3.1 it is very unlikely that it will be the weak link in the chain. Here you can see the SSD, despite being really fast, has become the slowest component in use and thus the bottleneck in drive speed.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"> </p>
<p style="text-align: left;">As depicted by the above examples, you can clearly see how the weak link in the chain will hold back all of the other components.<br><br>The most common weak link that we see is the drive component. Your standard 5600rpm HDD will run around 115MB/s. All common connection interfaces easily exceed that speed, USB3.0 is faster (420MB/s), Thunderbolt 1 is faster (1000MB/s), USB3.1 is faster (1000MB/s) and Thunderbolt 3 is a lot faster (5000MB/s).<br><br>When dealing with SSDs the story is a little different. Most SATA SSDs will run around 520MB/s. When this SSD is connected via USB3.0 you will be capped out by the limitations of USB3.0 (420MB/s), but if you use the same drive via USB3.1 (1000MB/s) you will be once again limited by the drive speed, even though its a fast, solid state drive.<br><br>When considering hard drive speed you should first consider your drive (HDD/SSD), then your connection interface (USB, Thunderbolt) followed by your cables, adapters and computer connection interface. The SATA Status of an enclosure is the last thing that I check as it's only a factor in rare circumstances.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">WILL THUNDERBOLT MAKE MY DRIVE FASTER?<br></span></strong></h1>
<p>With all of that said, we land back at our original question. Will Thunderbolt Make My Drive Faster? If you read and understood this article, I'm sure you'd be able to answer that yourself. But allow me to elaborate on my original answer for the sake of being thorough: 'Sometimes, but in most circumstances it won't make a difference.'<br><br>Thunderbolt is a connection interface. Indeed there are times where having a Thunderbolt Hard Drive over a USB3.0 Hard Drive will make your drive faster, but this will only occur where all other pillars of hard drive performance exceed the speed of the USB3.0 connection interface. So you need to ask yourself, when will a drive (HDD/SSD) exceed Thunderbolt 1 (1000MB/s), Thunderbolt 2 (2000MB/s) or Thunderbolt 3 (4000MB/s)? The prime example is SSDs, but you may also see high performance drives in RAID Systems. All SSDs will cap out on USB3.0 and require a faster connection interface to achieve peak performance, so in this instance you need Thunderbolt or USB3.1 to get the most out of that particular SSD.<br><br>When I have been asked the question of Thunderbolt Drives it has been in relation to HDDs, specifically 5600rpm HDDs which cap out around 115MB/s. Being that all modern connection interfaces exceed the 115MB/s limit of the drive itself, it doesn't matter if we are using USB3.0, Thunderbolt 1, Thunderbolt 2, USB3.1 or even Firewire 800. That drive will perform the same via any of those connections.<br><br>So for those of you that have been fooled into thinking a Thunderbolt Hard Drive will perform better or offload faster, think twice and ask if it's got an SSD inside. If not, like in most circumstances, being Thunderbolt won't make a difference at all.</p>
</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong></strong></div>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;"> MERELY A GLIMPSE<br></span></strong></h1>
<p>For some this may seem like an information overload, particularly when it gets technical. But this is merely a glimpse down the rabbit hole. In order to understand on an even deeper level, there are many other facets that need to be explored. I'll make brief mention of them below as reference for anyone who may want more information. Rest assured, these will be covered in-depth in a future blog post.</p>
<ul>
<li>Power Delivery is important. Most hard drives will suffice on bus power (5W-12W) but some will require more power from an external source. All explanations above are based on adequate power delivery to the hard drive.</li>
<li>There are many flavours of HDD. 2.5" and 3.5", 5400RPM through to 7200rpm. These form factors and components have an impact on speed. In this article we are primarily talking about 5600RPM HDDs which is what you will see in most portable hard drives off the shelf.</li>
<li>SSDs come in many flavours as well. There are SATA SSDs which we discussed in this article, but also the newer M.2 SSDs and PCIe SSDs, both of which deliver significant speed improvements.</li>
<li>The concept of connection interfaces is quite in-depth. We need to address M.2 and PCIe Internal Connections as opposed to just SATA which we discussed here. In terms of External Connection Interfaces the differences in power delivery, different connectors and ports as well as the difference between Theoretical Speed and Actual Speed all needs to be discussed.</li>
<li>What happens to the bridge after the connection to your computer? Your USB-C or Thunderbolt 3 Port connects directly to your computers motherboard which has it's own limitations in terms of PCIe Lanes and how it allocates speed and resources. While this rarely is a factor in the throttling of hard drive speeds it's valuable information that you should know.</li>
</ul>
<p>So I leave you with a new understanding of hard drive theory and hopefully with some practical knowledge that you can apply to your work. As I said, this is the tip of the iceberg. If there is anything you want to know specifically or in more detail, please let us know in the comments section below.<br><br>Thanks!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/where-do-i-find-my-film-drives-serial-number</id>
    <published>2018-11-20T12:58:00+11:00</published>
    <updated>2018-11-20T13:14:00+11:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/where-do-i-find-my-film-drives-serial-number"/>
    <title>WHERE DO I FIND MY FILM DRIVES &apos;SERIAL NUMBER&apos;?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Bradley Andrew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<div style="text-align: left;">Recently we launched our <a href="https://filmdrives.com/pages/speed-lookup" title="Speed Lookup">Film Drives 'Speed Lookup' Tool</a> that allows you to enter the Serial Number from any Film Drive and instantly access the Write and Read Speeds that it recorded during testing at the factory. You might be asking, where exactly do I find my Film Drives Serial Number? So we thought we'd show you. <strong></strong><br><strong></strong>
</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong></strong></div>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">HARD DRIVE<br></span></strong></h1>
<p>Every hard drive that we manufacture gets labelled with a unique SN. This short video will show you where to find it on the <a href="https://filmdrives.com/products/film-drives-one" title="Film Drives 'ONE'">Film Drives 'ONE'</a> and <a href="https://filmdrives.com/products/film-drives-two" title="Film Drives 'TWO'">Film Drives 'TWO'</a>.</p>
<div style="position: relative; height: 0; padding-bottom: 56.25%;"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ue80bqabLaU?vq=hd720" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0"></iframe></div>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">SET READY CASE<br></span></strong></h1>
<p>You'll also find the SN located on the Film Drives 'Set Ready Case' that comes with every <a href="https://filmdrives.com/products/film-drives-one" title="Film Drives 'ONE'">Film Drives 'ONE'</a> and <a href="https://filmdrives.com/products/film-drives-two" title="Film Drives 'TWO'">Film Drives 'TWO'</a>. It's located on the slip out label that sits within the plastic pocket.</p>
<div style="position: relative; height: 0; padding-bottom: 56.25%;"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mwnkNgibM1Q?vq=hd720" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0"></iframe></div>
<p> </p>
<p>Now that you know where your SN is located, feel free to give our <a href="https://filmdrives.com/pages/speed-lookup" title="Speed Lookup">Speed Lookup Tool</a> a go!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://filmdrives.com/pages/speed-lookup" title="Speed Lookup"><img alt="Speed Lookup" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Speed_Lookup_Border_large.jpg?v=1542679983" style="float: none;"></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"> </p>
<p>Thoughts or feedback? Let us know in the comments section below!</p>
<p>Thanks!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/optimizing-finder-for-data-management</id>
    <published>2018-09-27T16:00:00+10:00</published>
    <updated>2018-09-27T16:02:30+10:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/optimizing-finder-for-data-management"/>
    <title>OPTIMIZING FINDER FOR DATA MANAGEMENT</title>
    <author>
      <name>Bradley Andrew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<div>When prepping your computer for on-set data management there are many things that need to be setup. This can include software installations, application preferences, testing hardware, etc. One thing that is often overlooked is Finder in macOS. When you take a second to really think about it, this is data tool number one. I use it every day and I'm certain anyone that has ever professionally managed camera rushes has used Finder in some way, shape or form. This is a quick and easy tutorial on how to optimize Finder for macOS to serve you better.<br><br>
</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">DEFAULTS</span></strong></h1>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;"></span></strong>When macOS is freshly installed on your system Finder will conform to Apple's Default Settings. These settings are fine but they fit in with a minimalist approach to information which isn't ideal when your job is an astute attention to detail.</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p>In the below image I have setup a 'Rushes Drive' and a 'Backup Drive' for the purpose of this tutorial. You'll always be backing up to at least two drives, preferably three. I keep my file naming conventions consistent throughout drives, the only naming that differs is when it's a different drive or different shoot day.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/macOS_Default_1024x1024.jpg?v=1538017061" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">My questions to the above Finder Setup would be:</p>
<ul>
<li>How can I tell which Finder Window corresponds to which drive?</li>
<li>How can I tell how much space is left on the hard drive?</li>
<li>When dealing with camera media, how many items are in this folder?</li>
</ul>
<p>You could check all of this is you use Get Info (Command + I) on the folder you are looking at. But this is time consuming and an extra process for you to complete just to get information that can be easily displayed. There must be a better way, thankfully there is!</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">OPTIMIZATION<br>PART 01</span></strong></h1>
<p>In order to fully optimize Finder you will need to download a handy piece of software. There is a free application for macOS called <a href="https://www.titanium-software.fr/en/onyx.html" target="_blank" title="Onyx for macOS" rel="noopener noreferrer">Onyx</a> that serves as a tool for system maintenance as well as tweaking advanced user settings. Each version of <a href="https://www.titanium-software.fr/en/onyx.html" target="_blank" title="Onyx for macOS" rel="noopener noreferrer">Onyx</a> is specifically built for different iterations of macOS. Please download the version of Onyx that is applicable to your OS. For this example I am using Onyx 3.4.9 for macOS High Sierra 10.13.6.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Onyx_Icon_97dfe18c-e449-42c6-9092-bf5d0b71c388_medium.jpg?v=1538018870" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>When you open Onyx it will run a few system checks, please click continue and allow it to complete this process. Once you are in, select the 'Parameters' Icon in the user bar which will take you to Advanced User Settings. From here select the tab labelled 'Finder'.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Onyx_1024x1024.jpg?v=1538018675" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The key setting for our purposes here is under 'Misc. Options'. Please tick the checkbox next to 'Show the item path in the window title'.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Onyx_Option_1024x1024.jpg?v=1538018674" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">You will get a pop-up box saying that Onyx needs to close and re-open Finder. Ensure no files are copying in the background and click continue.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Onyx_Popup_large.jpg?v=1538018439" alt=""></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Now when you look at the exact same drives detailed above they will look like this:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Title_Bar_Tweaked_With_Onyx_1024x1024.jpg?v=1538019931" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The key difference is the Title Bar. Take a look at the A/B Comparison below:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Title_Bar_Comparison_1024x1024.jpg?v=1538020420" style="float: none;"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p style="text-align: left;">Before the tweak with Onyx it just displayed the folder name, now it displays the full path of the folder. This means that you will always be able to tell exactly where the folder/file you are looking at is located, all in a quick glance.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">This becomes super useful when you are working with multiple drives as offload destinations, all it takes is a mis-click and you'll wind up navigating to a different drive. As they all tend to follow the same file structure it isn't obvious what exact drive you are looking at. This is crucial when you want to ensure specific footage is copied to a particular drive. I often run Finder side by side with my data management software to act as a double check encase the software or a human error hasn't offloaded the footage to the destination that I intended. The more redundancies you have built into your data management process the more bulletproof your work will be.</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">OPTIMIZATION<br>PART 02</span></strong></h1>
<p style="text-align: left;">This second optimization doesn't require any 3rd Party Software. All you need to do is open any Finder Window, select 'View' from the top left Application Bar and select 'Show Status Bar'. This can also be toggled on/off with the keyboard shortcut 'Command + /'.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Show_Status_Bar_large.jpg?v=1538021659" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Once you have applied this tweak the Finder Windows that we were using above will now look like this:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Status_Bar_Enabled_1024x1024.jpg?v=1538021807" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Before you had no information, now you have the item count of the current folder as well as how much space is left on the drive you are looking at.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The item count is useful when checking camera cards, you've got 42 clips, Finder says 42 items in the folder that you are looking at which would be the folder your data management software has offloaded to. That's another double check method to make sure there hasn't been an issue anywhere else in your process.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The remaining space is helpful to see at a glance to ensure you're keeping track of exactly how much you have shot and how much you can still offload onto your current drives. Some days there is just an onslaught of data and you are constantly offloading, when your main priority is staying on top of cards as they come in, a quick look at this status bar is invaluable. It will inform you if you need to swap out to a new set of drives soon, or if you don't have a new set of drives to flag it with the Production Manager to ensure something can be sorted out before it's too late. </p>
<p> </p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">THE macOS ALTERNATIVE</span></strong></h1>
<p style="text-align: left;">There is an alternate option to 'Optimization Part 01' that was detailed above which doesn't require the 3rd Party Software 'Onyx'. I must acknowledge those who are well versed with Finder that may be asking 'What about the Path Bar?'. </p>
<p style="text-align: left;">As simple as displaying the Status Bar, you can open any Finder Window, select 'View' from the top left Application Bar and select 'Show Path Bar'. This can also be toggled on/off with the keyboard shortcut 'Option + Command + /'.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Show_Path_Bar_large.jpg?v=1538022814" style="float: none;"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p style="text-align: center;"><span>Once you have enabled the Path Bar the Finder Windows that we were using above will now look like this:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Path_Bar_Enabled_1024x1024.jpg?v=1538022989" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">This may work for some users as it displays the current path in a more graphical fashion, see below for Onyx Method vs. macOS Method:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Onyx_Vs_macOS_1024x1024.jpg?v=1538023684" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">But for me I find that the 'Show Path Bar' Option takes up too much screen real estate, particularly when working on smaller screens like a laptop. I would much rather have my file path displayed in the title, the title is going to be there regardless, if I can hit two birds with one stone, that being title bar and path bar in one then that's a win in my book.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">I also find that it can be too busy when combined with the Status Bar. There is a fine line between not enough information and too much information. I find the macOS Path Bar to be that fine line.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/All_Enabled_1024x1024.jpg?v=1538023175" style="float: none;"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>OTHER TWEAKS</strong></span></h1>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Finder View</strong></span></p>
<p>Some users may prefer to use a different Finder View. These can be accessed by opening<span> any Finder Window, select 'View' from the top left Application Bar and select a View:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/View_Options_large.jpg?v=1538024289" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Alternatively you can use the View Icons which are located in the top bar of every Finder Window:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/View_Icons_large.jpg?v=1538024464" alt=""></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">You can also use the keyboard shortcut Command + 1/2/3/4 to toggle between Views.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">I prefer the Icons View as my default view for Finder. It allows your browsing to be more visual which I find useful when navigating through camera rushes in Finder. The downside is that you can only jump forward/back one folder at a time, this can be a pain for complex file structures with many layers of folders that you need to move through constantly. The back function can be accessed from the 'Back Button' in the top left bar of every Finder Window. If you'd like to use the back function more fluently you can use the keyboard shortcut 'Command + ['.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Occasionally I will flick to the Columns View in Finder. This remedies the navigation problem when you are deep in complex file structures. It also allows for a list view of files which is useful when looking at image sequences or an overview of 50+ Clips within a single folder.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Columns_View_1024x1024.jpg?v=1538025372" style="float: none;"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>Force Filename Extensions</strong></span></p>
<p>Some files don't display their extension by default. There is an option that will force all files viewed in Finder to display their filename extension. To enable it navigate to Finder -&gt; Preferences.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Finder_Prefs_large.jpg?v=1538025671" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Select the 'Advanced' Icon in the user bar. Tick the checkbox next to 'Show all filename extensions'. This option will now be enabled.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Filename_Extensions_large.jpg?v=1538025681" alt=""></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Say you have an image that appears as 'Image' in Finder, when this option is selected it will now display that file as 'Image.jpg' instead. This let's you easily see the file extension of a particular file. It's not required under all circumstances but is an option worth knowing about should you deal with files that don't natively display their extension.</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">CONCLUSION</span></strong></h1>
<p style="text-align: left;">When I setup a new computer with macOS for Data Management these Finder options are some of the first that I tweak. I trust these options will serve you well, as they have served me well over the many thousands of terabytes that I have transferred through my computer.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">As always, if you have any questions or comments, please reach out below!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/2018-macbook-pro-egpu-faster-transcoding</id>
    <published>2018-08-05T10:00:00+10:00</published>
    <updated>2018-08-05T11:03:48+10:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/2018-macbook-pro-egpu-faster-transcoding"/>
    <title>2018 MACBOOK PRO + EGPU = FASTER TRANSCODING?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Bradley Andrew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<div style="text-align: left;">In 2016 the MacBook Pro got updated with a new design and beefier specs, but the specs were never really <span style="text-decoration: underline;">pro</span>. Finally in 2018 Apple issued an update that finally ticked the boxes for a worthy upgrade.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"> </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">6-Core CPU, check.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;">32GB of RAM, check.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;">Decent Graphics Card, check.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"> </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">I jumped at the chance to refresh my Data Management Kit with an up to date system. But stock standard is never enough for me, with macOS now supporting eGPUs it got me thinking that there is an even better way to do things. I had a <a href="https://www.gigabyte.com/us/Graphics-Card/GV-N98TG1-GAMING-6GD#ov" target="_blank" title="980Ti" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nvidia 980Ti</a> sitting around and decided to fit it to an <a href="https://www.akitio.com/expansion/node-pro" target="_blank" title="Akitio Node Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Akitio Node Pro eGPU Enclosure</a>. Time to put the new rig through some tests!<br><br>
</div>
<div style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/AkitioNodePro_L_grande.jpg?v=1533429091" style="float: none;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"></div>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">THE QUESTION</span></strong></h1>
<p><strong><span style="color: #000000;"></span></strong>What I am gunning for with these tests is to see if it's viable to use the Internal GPU which is an <a href="https://www.amd.com/en/products/graphics/radeon-rx-560x" target="_blank" title="AMD Radeon Pro 560X" rel="noopener noreferrer">AMD Radeon Pro 560X</a> and the <a href="https://www.gigabyte.com/us/Graphics-Card/GV-N98TG1-GAMING-6GD#ov" target="_blank" title="980Ti" rel="noopener noreferrer">eGPU Nvidia 980Ti</a> simultaneously in <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve Studio" rel="noopener noreferrer">Resolve Studio</a> to get faster transcode speeds from the 2018 MacBook Pro.</p>
<p>If possible, it would allow for a really portable transcoding solution on-set. You'd have a laptop which would produce modest transcode results, then you could easily plug up your eGPU to take those speeds to the next level. The plan would be to use the Internal GPU for transcoding when you didn't have Mains Power, if you did have Mains Power you'd be able to use both the Internal GPU and eGPU to power through the transcodes at record speed.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/LaptopAndNode_ALT_L_grande.jpg?v=1533429454" alt=""></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">TEST PROCEDURE</span></strong></h1>
<p>For this test I used a top of the line 2018 MacBook Pro with the following specs:</p>
<p><strong>CPU:</strong> 2.9GHz Intel i9<br><strong>GPU:</strong> AMD Radeon Pro 560X / Intel UHD Graphics 630<br><strong>RAM:</strong> 32GB<br><strong>SSD</strong>: 1TB PCIe</p>
<p>The eGPU was an <a href="https://www.akitio.com/expansion/node-pro" target="_blank" title="Akitio Node Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Akitio Node Pro</a> fitted with a <a href="https://www.gigabyte.com/us/Graphics-Card/GV-N98TG1-GAMING-6GD#ov" target="_blank" title="Gigabyte 980 Ti" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gigabyte GeForce GTX 980Ti</a> connected via Thunderbolt 3 to the MacBook Pro. To make the 980Ti compatible with macOS I used the <a href="https://github.com/learex/macOS-eGPU/tree/master#macos-egpush" target="_blank" title="macOS eGPU Script" rel="noopener noreferrer">macOS-eGPU.sh script</a>.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/AkitioNodePro_Int_L_grande.jpg?v=1533429090" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>Transcodes were conducted with DaVinci Resolve 15 Beta 6 for Single GPU Tests and DaVinci Resolve Studio 15 Beta 7 for Dual GPU Tests.</p>
<p>Transcodes were working with these input/output formats:<br><strong>Source Format:</strong> 4K UHD 3840x2160 ARRIRAW from an Alexa LF<br><strong>Output Format:</strong> HD 1920x1080 ProRes 422 HQ with a LogC to REC709 LUT Applied</p>
<p>Footage was courtesy of <a href="http://www.arri.com/" target="_blank" title="ARRI" rel="noopener noreferrer">ARRI</a> from their <a href="http://www.arri.com/camera/alexa/learn/alexa_sample_footage/" target="_blank" title="Alexa LF Sample Footage" rel="noopener noreferrer">sample footage collection</a>. The exact clips used from the collection were B002C006 and B003C001. These clips were duplicated 3 Times in the Resolve Timeline to create a total length of source material to be processed of 2:14:09 @ 24fps, aka 2 Mins 14 Secs 9 Frames. ARRIRAW was chosen for these tests as it frequently requires transcoding and is heavily influenced by the performance of a Graphics Card.</p>
<p>Both source footage and exported footage was reading/writing from the MacBook Pro's Internal PCIe SSD which delivers speeds of over 2000MB/s thus negating hard disk speed as a limiting factor in the transcode pipeline.</p>
<p>All tests were conducted in identical conditions. The only settings changed were GPU Processing Mode and which GPU was being used. Settings can be tweaked in Resolve's Preferences and will come into effect once you reboot the software.<strong><span style="color: #000000;"></span></strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Resolve_Setup_grande.jpg?v=1533366196" style="float: none;"></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">TEST RESULTS</span></strong></h1>
<p style="text-align: center;">This is the raw data from my tests:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/TranscodeTest_Data_1024x1024.jpg?v=1533364279" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">This is a comparison of the Transcode FPS between different GPU Modes and GPUs:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/TranscodeTest_Graph_FPS_1024x1024.jpg?v=1533364280" style="float: none;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">This is a comparison of the Transcode Time in minutes between different GPU Modes and GPUs:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/TranscodeTest_Graph_Time_1024x1024.jpg?v=1533364281" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>When you transcode ARRIRAW through <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">DaVinci Resolve</a> using the Metal GPU Mode with a Nvidia GPU you will get corrupt looking images as <a href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/is-my-drone-footage-corrupt" target="_blank" title="IS MY DRONE FOOTAGE CORRUPT?" rel="noopener noreferrer">explained in a previous blog post</a>. These corrupt looking colour shifts not only display while transcoding in Resolve but they also come through in the exported file. While I did test Metal for speed with the 980Ti, the product of the transcode is unusable and thus the Metal results should be ignored. Transcodes that are effected by GPU Corruption look like this when running in Resolve:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Metal_980Ti_Small_grande.jpg?v=1533366455" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>These results were much more interesting then anticipated. ARRIRAW is a GPU dependent video codec so it's no surprise that a beefier GPU performed better. What is interesting is that the CUDA API is significantly faster at processing ARRIRAW than the OpenCL API. Even in the instance where I was using Dual GPUs to process the footage in OpenCL the Single Nvidia GPU using CUDA was still faster. 36fps vs. 54fps. It's a big difference, especially when processing massive amounts of footage. If you could complete the exact same task in 1:02 Mins or 1:32 Mins what would you do?</p>
<p>Worth noting is that each and every time the transcode speed was capped out by the GPU Processor. Not the GPU Memory and not the CPU. I used <a href="https://bjango.com/mac/istatmenus/" target="_blank" title="iStat Menus" rel="noopener noreferrer">iStat Menus</a> to verify this which you can see below highlighted in red:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/GPU_Comparison_grande.jpg?v=1533365931" style="float: none;"></p>
<p> The lesson to be learnt here is that many people just see the number when referencing the GPU. '6GB GPU, wow, that must be fast'. Well yes, it is fast but that number isn't the be all and end all for producing faster results, particulary while transcoding.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">CONCLUSION</span></strong></h1>
<p>The hypothesis was to see if the addition of a eGPU could drastically speed up transcode times while having a small footprint on set. I'd say the answer is yes but the results didn't appear in the way that was expected.</p>
<p>Without a eGPU you can transcode ARRIRAW on the MacBook Pro at 19-20fps depending if you use OpenCL or Metal. Once you plug in a eGPU fitted with a 980Ti you can transcode using CUDA at 54fps which is 2.7x faster. A worthy improvement in my book. Going forward I'll have the eGPU in my kit as a portable option for boosting transcode performance.</p>
<p>I'll also be sure to use the CUDA API where available for transcoding ARRIRAW as it has proven superior for crunching the 1's and 0's when working with ARRI's flagship recording codec.</p>
<p>The eGPU is a flexible tool. You can fit almost any Graphics Card in a eGPU, I just happened to have a spare <a href="https://www.gigabyte.com/us/Graphics-Card/GV-N98TG1-GAMING-6GD#ov" target="_blank" title="980Ti" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nvidia 980Ti</a> around and thus it became my weapon of choice. If I were selecting a specific Graphics Card for the purposes of transcoding with an Apple Computer there are some other attractive options that work natively with macOS that you should consider taking a look into. You could use the <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/blackmagicegpu/" target="_blank" title="Blackmagic eGPU" rel="noopener noreferrer">Blackmagic eGPU</a> which comes pre-fitted with a <a href="https://www.amd.com/en/graphics/workstations-radeon-pro-500" target="_blank" title="AMD Radeon Pro Series" rel="noopener noreferrer">Radeon Pro 580</a>. Alternatively you could use the <a href="https://www.akitio.com/expansion/node-pro" target="_blank" title="Akitio Node Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Akitio Node Pro eGPU Enclosure</a> that I am using but fit it with the same GPU that is used in an iMac Pro, the <a href="https://www.amd.com/en/products/graphics/radeon-rx-vega-56" target="_blank" title="AMD Vega 56" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vega 56</a> or <a href="https://www.amd.com/en/products/graphics/radeon-rx-vega-64" target="_blank" title="AMD Vega 64" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vega 64</a>. These Graphics Cards have official support from Apple in macOS and will likely produce different results to those documented above, particularly with Dual Internal GPU and eGPU Setups using the OpenCL and Metal APIs. If you've got an eGPU running any of these GPU Setups we'd love to hear from you in the comments below.</p>
<p>I hope you've found this useful. Questions, comments, want help? Touch base in the comments section below!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/is-my-drone-footage-corrupt</id>
    <published>2018-07-14T11:23:00+10:00</published>
    <updated>2018-07-14T13:24:57+10:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/is-my-drone-footage-corrupt"/>
    <title>IS MY DRONE FOOTAGE CORRUPT?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Bradley Andrew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<div style="text-align: left;">Over the past few years we've witnessed the rise of Drone Cinematography on-set. While this has brought new and exciting tools into the hands of many filmmakers, it's also caused an equal number of headaches for DITs and Data Wranglers. Today I want to show you how to solve the number one problem that I've encountered when working with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CinemaDNG" target="_blank" title="CinemaDNG Files" rel="noopener noreferrer">CinemaDNG Files</a> from <a href="https://www.dji.com/products/professional?site=brandsite&amp;from=nav#camera-gimbal" target="_blank" title="Zenmuse Gimbal Cameras" rel="noopener noreferrer">DJI's Zenmuse</a> line of cameras, including the <a href="https://www.dji.com/zenmuse-x7?site=brandsite&amp;from=nav" target="_blank" title="Zenmuse X7" rel="noopener noreferrer">X7</a> and <a href="https://www.dji.com/zenmuse-x5?site=brandsite&amp;from=nav" target="_blank" title="Zenmuse X5" rel="noopener noreferrer">X5</a>.</div>
<div style="text-align: center;"></div>
<div style="text-align: center;"></div>
<div style="text-align: center;"></div>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">DJI INSPIRE AND ZENMUSE</span></strong></h1>
<p>Short of Big Rig Custom Drones that can take an Alexa or RED Camera Package, the <a href="https://www.dji.com/inspire-2?site=brandsite&amp;from=nav" target="_blank" title="DJI Inspire 2" rel="noopener noreferrer">DJI Inspire Series</a> is one of the most common drones that you will encounter on-set. They are small, compact, portable and fully capable of taking a high quality camera package in the form of the <a href="https://www.dji.com/zenmuse-x7?site=brandsite&amp;from=nav" target="_blank" title="Zenmuse X7" rel="noopener noreferrer">Zenmuse X7</a> or <a href="https://www.dji.com/zenmuse-x5?site=brandsite&amp;from=nav" target="_blank" title="Zenmuse X5" rel="noopener noreferrer">X5</a>.</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Inspire_Drone_large.jpg?v=1531534531" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>These cameras record in two professional quality formats, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_ProRes" target="_blank" title="ProRes" rel="noopener noreferrer">ProRes</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CinemaDNG" target="_blank" title="CinemaDNG" rel="noopener noreferrer">CinemaDNG</a>. As the CinemaDNG Format offers great resolution as well as the flexibility of Camera RAW it's often the preferred recording codec of many DPs. Though it's with the CinemaDNG Codec that the challenges begin to arise.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">CINEMA DNG</span></strong></h1>
<p>For today's explanation I am going to use some sample footage provided by DJI. Please head over to the <a href="https://www.dji.com/zenmuse-x7/info#downloads" target="_blank" title="Download Section" rel="noopener noreferrer">Download Section</a> of the <a href="https://www.dji.com/zenmuse-x7?site=brandsite&amp;from=nav" target="_blank" title="Zenmuse X7" rel="noopener noreferrer">DJI Zenmuse X7 Page</a> and download the file titled <a href="https://dl.djicdn.com/downloads/zenmuse+x7/20171027/Footage_01.zip" target="_blank" title="Zenmuse X7 Sample Footage" rel="noopener noreferrer">'X7 CinemaDNG Sample File 1'</a>.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Resolve_with_CUDA_Processing_grande.jpg?v=1531530462" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; float: none;"></p>
<p>This is a drone tracking shot of 3 Motorcyclists. It has been shot at 6K (5760x3240) in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CinemaDNG" target="_blank" title="CinemaDNG" rel="noopener noreferrer">CinemaDNG Format</a>. The running length is 3 Secs 8 Frames at 25fps or 83 Frames Total. When you look at the footage in macOS Finder it appears as follows:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CinemaDNG_in_Finder_grande.jpg?v=1531528768" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; float: none;"></p>
<p>What you can see here is that CinemaDNG Files are presented as an Image Sequence. One CinemaDNG File corresponds to a single frame of footage. Image Sequences are great, they are often used in VFX Pipelines as it allows single frames to be rendered simultaneously on various different machines, a massive time saver.</p>
<p>When working with this DNG Image Sequence as a DIT or Data Wrangler, you not only need to transfer, verify and backup the footage but you'll also need to do a bit of Quality Control (QC). So how do you play back an image sequence to complete your QC? I recommend <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">DaVinci Resolve</a>, an <a href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/whats-in-a-data-kit" target="_blank" title="What's In A Data Kit?" rel="noopener noreferrer">essential tool in any Data Management Kit</a>.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">HOT TIP:</span></strong></h1>
<p>When working with any Image Sequence File Format (Zenmuse CinemaDNG / ARRIRAW from an Alexa XT) make sure you are offloading with XXHash Checksums in <a href="http://www.imagineproducts.com/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;products_id=59" target="_blank" title="Shotput Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Shotput Pro</a> or <a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silverstack</a>.</p>
<p>Checksum algorithms verify every single file that is being copied. This is fine when you have 10 Quicktime Files per camera card, you only need to checksum 10 Files. But when you are working with an Image Sequence every single frame is a file, so the equivalent of those 10 Quicktime Files might be in the realm of 100,000 Image Files. Meaning you have to checksum 100,000 Files which increases offload time significantly. XXHash is the fastest checksum method and should be your go-to for image sequences. It can mean the difference between a 1 Hour Offload with XX Hash vs a 2.5 Hour Offload with MD5.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">CINEMA DNG IN DAVINCI RESOLVE</span></strong></h1>
<p style="text-align: center;">Have you ever imported footage from a <a href="https://www.dji.com/zenmuse-x7?site=brandsite&amp;from=nav" target="_blank" title="Zenmuse X7" rel="noopener noreferrer">Zenmuse X7</a> or <a href="https://www.dji.com/zenmuse-x5?site=brandsite&amp;from=nav" target="_blank" title="Zenmuse X5" rel="noopener noreferrer">X5</a> and have it playback like this in <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">DaVinci Resolve</a>?</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Resolve_with_Metal_Processing_grande.jpg?v=1531529572" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; float: none;"></p>
<p>I certainly have. It makes you worry. Alarm bells ring raising all sorts of red flags. You think that the data is corrupt, there is an issue with the file. You double check the copied file size with Finder, yup, it matches the source footage on the camera card. You try playback directly from the camera card, it still looks corrupt. You open a single image file in Photoshop...wait, it looks fine here. What is going on?</p>
<p>I'll tell you what. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CinemaDNG" target="_blank" title="CinemaDNG" rel="noopener noreferrer">CinemaDNG Codec</a> is a very GPU Intensive Codec, meaning that the ability to play it back in real-time usually depends on the grunt of your Graphics Card, both it's processor speed and it's memory. The faster your GPU the better you'll be able to playback CinemaDNG Files.</p>
<p>Does that mean a slow GPU can't playback CinemaDNG Files? No.</p>
<p>Does that means a slow GPU causes the image to look corrupt? No.</p>
<p>It all comes down to GPU Processing Mode. That is the cause of the problem here.</p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">GPU PROCESSING MODE</span></strong></h1>
<p>You may have heard of terms like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenCL" target="_blank" title="OpenCL" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenCL</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CUDA" target="_blank" title="CUDA" rel="noopener noreferrer">CUDA</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metal_(API)" target="_blank" title="Metal" rel="noopener noreferrer">Metal</a>. What they refer to are APIs, software that interfaces with your computers graphics card. Think of it as a bridge between your hardware and software.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">DaVinci Resolve</a> the default GPU Processing Mode is 'Auto'. This lets the computer pick from OpenCL, CUDA or Metal at it's whim. You will find this setting by selecting DaVinci Resolve -&gt; Preferences -&gt; Configuration from the Menu Bar.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Resolve_Config_Auto_grande.jpg?v=1531531047" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; float: none;"></p>
<p>Through troubleshooting and testing I have been able to determine that the Metal GPU Processing Mode is the cause of the corrupt looking images that appear when playing back Zenmuse CinemaDNG Footage in DaVinci Resolve. When Resolve is set to it's stock setting of 'Auto', it uses Apple's Metal API for certain GPUs, which causes the problem depicted above.</p>
<p>This problem doesn't effect all GPUs. It doesn't occur on my iMac which is running an <a href="https://www.geforce.com/hardware/notebook-gpus/geforce-gt-755m" target="_blank" title="Nvidia GeForce GT 755M" rel="noopener noreferrer">Internal NVidia GeForce GT 755M GPU</a> but I've had it occur on my MacBook Pro using the <a href="https://www.geforce.com/hardware/notebook-gpus/geforce-gt-650m" target="_blank" title="NVidia GeForce GT 650M" rel="noopener noreferrer">Internal NVidia GeForce GT 650M GPU</a> as well as bigger rigs running a <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/geforce/products/10series/geforce-gtx-1080-ti/" target="_blank" title="1080Ti" rel="noopener noreferrer">1080Ti</a> or a <a href="https://www.geforce.com/hardware/desktop-gpus/geforce-gtx-980-ti" target="_blank" title="980Ti" rel="noopener noreferrer">980Ti</a>.</p>
<p>So if you've got Resolve setup using its stock configuration and don't have a problem, great. If you are having an issue, thankfully the fix is easy. Simply navigate  DaVinci Resolve -&gt; Preferences -&gt; Configuration from the Menu Bar and change the GPU Processing Mode to 'CUDA' or 'OpenCL'. You'll need to restart DaVinci Resolve for this change to come into effect.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/GPU_Processing_Mode_grande.jpg?v=1531531657" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; float: none;"></p>
<p>Once the software has been restarted all of your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CinemaDNG" target="_blank" title="CinemaDNG" rel="noopener noreferrer">CinemaDNG Footage</a> from the <a href="https://www.dji.com/zenmuse-x7?site=brandsite&amp;from=nav" target="_blank" title="Zenmuse X7" rel="noopener noreferrer">Zenmuse Camera</a> should work without any issue. You may just suffer laggy playback is you are using a computer with a slower GPU.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Metal_and_CUDA_1024x1024.jpg?v=1531531966" style="display: block; float: none; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p> </p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">TRANSCODING</span></strong></h1>
<p>When I first encountered this issue I thought it may have just been a display problem within DaVinci Resolve. So I did a transcode of the footage to test that theory and the Graphics Issue carried over to the transcode. Super scary! This is a video of the transcoding results using the different GPU Processing Modes: </p>
<p> </p>
<div style="position: relative; height: 0; padding-bottom: 56.25%;"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tGqqyqaNrEQ?ecver=2;vq=HD720%E2%80%9D%20width=" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" style="position: absolute; width: 100%; height: 100%; left: 0;" allowfullscreen="" height="360" frameborder="0"></iframe></div>
<p> </p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">CONCLUSION</span></strong></h1>
<p>I have come across this issue many times over the years. It hadn't happened to me for a long while and just the other week when I was working with a Zenmuse X7 on an Inspire 2 the GPU Issue struck again. I did a Google to see what info I could find on this specific issue and the results were pretty much non-existent. So I decided to put together this post in hopes of helping someone else one day when they inevitably encounter this problem.</p>
<p>Thoughts or feedback? Let us know in the comments section below!</p>
<p>Till next time, I hope your data wrangling issues are far and few between.</p>
<p>Thanks!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/whats-in-a-data-kit</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T10:45:00+10:00</published>
    <updated>2018-04-30T16:21:41+10:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://filmdrives.com/blogs/blog/whats-in-a-data-kit"/>
    <title>WHAT&apos;S IN A DATA KIT?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Bradley Andrew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Today I am going to run you through all of the components that make up a great Data Management Kit. My philosophy is to have every tool in the toolkit, that way no matter what problem arises you have all the resources on hand to tackle it head on.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">The Data Kit that I outline below is my personal Data Kit. It has been built on years of experience and problem solving on-set. The best way to think about it is to break it down into three categories, <strong>'Hardware'</strong>, <strong>'Software'</strong> and <strong>'Accessories'</strong>. I will address each category individually and identify which items are absolute essentials and which are nice to have. Let's dive in!</span></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>HARDWARE</strong></span></h1>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><strong>LAPTOP<br></strong><strong><em>(Essential)</em></strong></span></h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"> The primary component on which the rest of the Data Management Kit is built upon is the laptop. The <a href="https://www.apple.com/au/macbook-pro/?afid=p238%7Csxl2d2joJ-dc_mtid_18707vxu38484_pcrid_235072527257_&amp;cid=aos-au-kwgo-mac--slid-" target="_blank" title="MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Apple MacBook Pro</a> is the industry standard for a Data Laptop but you have a few flavors that you can choose from. The first being <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/macbook-pro-retina-display-faq/" title="Old MacBook Pro" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Old MacBook Pro (Retina Display)</a> and <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/macbook-pro-touch-bar-faq/" target="_blank" title="New MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">New MacBook Pro (Touch Bar)</a>, the second being 15" or 13" Screen Size.</span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">OLDER RETINA MACBOOK PRO</span></strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">The <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/macbook-pro-retina-display-faq/" target="_blank" title="Old MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Older Style Retina MacBook Pro</a> is an absolute workhorse and holds up to this day. There were many iterations on this model between 2012 and 2015, over that time period it evolved from Thunderbolt 1 Ports to Thunderbolt 2 Ports, the CPUs and GPUs got upgrades and the internal solid state storage went from SATA to PCIe. It's main advantage in the current data landscape is the fact that is has native USB3.0 and Thunderbolt 1/2 Ports. The world is in a transition period from USB3.0 and Thunderbolt with a Mini Display Port Connector to the all in one USB-C Connector that sports USB3.1 and Thunderbolt 3. Many peripherals that you will use while data wrangling still rely on this legacy technology. The advantages of USB-C are clear but while the world catches up this still needs to be a consideration, it's infinitly easier to use your card readers and hard drives without additional adapters which is where this MacBook Pro really shines.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/macbook-pro-retina-display-faq/" target="_blank" title="Old MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/MacBookPro_02_grande.jpg?v=1524368709" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">NEW TOUCH BAR MACBOOK PRO</span></strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">The <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/macbook-pro-touch-bar-faq/" target="_blank" title="New MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">New Touch Bar MacBook Pro</a> is a solid machine. It's certainly equipped for the next generation with 4x USB-C Ports that support both Thunderbolt 3 and USB3.1, though this does come with some disadvantages. As the USB-C Port doubles as a charging port for the laptop you basically sacrifice one data port for the sake of power. In the <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/macbook-pro-retina-display-faq/" target="_blank" title="Old MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Old Style MacBook Pro</a> you had four data lanes, 2x USB3.0 and 2x Thunderbolt, in this <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/macbook-pro-touch-bar-faq/" target="_blank" title="New MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">New Style MacBook Pro</a> you have only three data lanes, 3x TB3/USB3.1 as one is tied up with charging. You also need to deal with that fact that this laptop is on the cutting edge of technology, meaning that you'll need adapters to use USB3.0 and Thunderbolt 2 Devices. Not a deal breaker as there are many options out there to split your USB-C Port into multiple USB3.0 and TB2 Ports but it does add additional clutter and complication to your data setup. One really cool advantage of this machine is that it can be <a href="https://www.cygnett.com/products/20-000mah-usb-c-power-bank-in-black" target="_blank" title="Cygnett USB-C Power Bank" rel="noopener noreferrer">charged from a power bank via USB-C</a>. This means that you could run this laptop all day with bus powered drives and never need external power, a big advantage for run and gun jobs where you are constantly moving from place to place.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/macbook-pro-touch-bar-faq/" target="_blank" title="New MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/MacBookPro_03_grande.jpg?v=1524368709" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">15" vs. 13"</span></strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">You could setup a data laptop with either of these screen sizes as they generally have identical connections but they don't have identical specs. In general the 15" MacBooks will have Quad-Core CPUs and slightly beefier GPUs than their 13" Dual-Core Equivalents. The higher specs won't have a huge impact on your day to day Data Wrangling but they will impact your output when you get asked to do a quick transcode for a job. It's always best to build your kit for the worst case scenario, this means top notch specs. Max out your CPU, GPU and RAM and get a decent amount of Internal SSD Storage (512GB). If you max out your specs when you buy you laptop new it will last many, many years. Computers do date as quick as they say but they certainly don't become redundant as quick as you think, particularly in the context of data management. The other thing to consider is the actual screen size, you'll have considerably more real estate on a 15" Screen than a 13" Screen. This makes your life much easier while working and is also better when a Director or DP comes over wanting to look at the rushes. Bigger isn't always better, but in this case it is.</span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">MY LAPTOP</span></strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">I'm currently using a <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/specs/macbook-pro-core-i7-2.6-15-mid-2012-retina-display-specs.html" target="_blank" title="My MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mid 2012 15" Retina MacBook Pro</a> and it's still going strong. It's equipped with a 2.6GHZ Quad Core CPU, 1GB GPU, 16GB RAM and 256GB SSD. The battery has been replaced to maintain optimal portability and I've replaced the thermal paste on the CPU/GPU for better thermal regulation. I clean the internals from time to time and run regular software maintenance to make sure it's always performing at it's peak.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/MacBookPro_01_grande.jpg?v=1524368707" alt=""></span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">UPS<br>(<em>Essential)</em></span></strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">The Uninterruptible Power Supply. An absolute must have item for every Data Management Kit and should be used all the time. You'll sometimes be running card readers or drives that require external power, running these through a UPS will save your offload should a circuit be tripped or the power get pulled. The basic idea is that you can't interrupt power flow. If you lose mains power your UPS will continue to provide power to your devices for a few minutes while you identify the problem and fix it. I've seen many inexperienced data wranglers operate without a UPS and get stitched up when they are 40 Mins into an offload and they lose power thus corrupting their backup. This means they have lost 40 Mins of offload time, a significant set back in data heavy environments. Don't make that mistake, get a UPS.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">I use an <a href="http://powerquality.eaton.com/3S700AU.aspx?cx=22&amp;GUID=140B676E-D455-4C52-8CF6-E4AD1F261E25" target="_blank" title="Eaton UPS" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eaton 3S 700 UPS</a> which I've had for a couple of years now. I really like that it has 6 Power Ports, 3 are UPS Protected and the other 3 Ports are just power pass through. This gives me enough UPS Ports for Data while having enough spare power ports to add battery chargers as well. This means I don't need additional power boards, just my UPS. Easy. You should also make sure you have a few 10 Amp Cables in your kit as well, if you get caught up with a backlog of data at the end of the day, the Electrics won't be too happy having to wait around for their cable, nor will production be too happy having to pay them overtime. Always setup data with your own power cables, that way no one else is affected if you need to do some overtime.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://powerquality.eaton.com/3S700AU.aspx?cx=22&amp;GUID=140B676E-D455-4C52-8CF6-E4AD1F261E25" target="_blank" title="Eaton UPS" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/UPS_grande.jpg?v=1524369601" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000000;"><strong>SOFTWARE</strong></span></h1>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;"><a href="http://www.imagineproducts.com/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;products_id=59" target="_blank" title="Shotput Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;">SHOTPUT PRO</a><br>(<em>Essential)</em></span></strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><a href="http://www.imagineproducts.com/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;products_id=59" target="_blank" title="Shotput Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Shotput Pro</a> is the backbone of many Data Kits all over the world. It's very simple to use, it's got a one off purchase cost and is incredibly reliable. It's used to facilitate data transfers, it can copy to multiple destinations and perform checksums on those offloads while generating basic reports. It can be setup with separate offloads for different cameras which is super handy for multi-camera jobs. I've used this software to manage data on hundreds of jobs over many years, I've used it on Single Camera Jobs, I've used it on 20 Camera Jobs. Buy it. Learn it. Use it.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.imagineproducts.com/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;products_id=59" target="_blank" title="Shotput Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Shotput_grande.jpg?v=1524533170" alt=""></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;"><a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;">SILVERSTACK</a><br><em>(Optional)</em></span></strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">In more recent times I have switched from using <a href="http://www.imagineproducts.com/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;products_id=59" target="_blank" title="Shotput Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Shotput Pro</a> to <a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silverstack</a>. <a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silverstack</a> offers a more advanced feature set than <a href="http://www.imagineproducts.com/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;products_id=59" target="_blank" title="Shotput Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Shotput</a> which can be super useful for bigger productions or when you're seeking to deliver higher quality output to your production. It has many built-in report options which can be customised with clip metadata, it has project management features, built-in false colour and peaking for quality control checks as well as the ability to do transcodes. Pretty amazing. It doesn't come cheap though, it runs on a subscription fee that comes in at roughly $800AUD/year. I needed to use <a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silverstack</a> for a specific job a few years back, once I got into it there was no turning back as it allowed me to deliver great reports at the end of each shooting day which production found invaluable.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Silverstack_grande.jpg?v=1524533885" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://hedge.video/" target="_blank" title="Hedge" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">HEDGE</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><a href="https://hedge.video/" target="_blank" title="Hedge" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hedge</a> is a relatively new data management software that competes with <a href="http://www.imagineproducts.com/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;products_id=59" target="_blank" title="Shotput Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Shotput Pro</a> and <a href="https://pomfort.com/silverstack/" target="_blank" title="Silverstack" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silverstack</a>. I haven't extensively tested it but have heard some great things about it's speed and reliability. It's got quite a modern design and a good development team behind it. I plan at taking a closer look at this in the future, when I do I'll be sure to let you know!</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://hedge.video/" target="_blank" title="Hedge" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Hedge_grande.jpg?v=1524533197" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">DAVINCI RESOLVE</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">This is the best free software that you will ever get. It's amazing. You get industry standard colour grading software that can output UHD, it works as a NLE, it has built in compositing with Fusion as well as audio editing. A must have for any Data Management Kit. I use it for transcoding, quality control checks, test grades and many other tasks that come up on a day to day basis.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Resolve_grande.jpg?v=1524533172" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://codex.online/software" target="_blank" title="Codex Software" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">CODEX VAULT PLATFORM</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">The <a href="https://codex.online/software" target="_blank" title="Codex Software" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex Vault Platform</a> is a must have for your Data Kit. You need this to setup the Codex VFS (Virtual File System) on your computer which is required to access ARRIRAW from an Alexa XT, SXT or LF. If you shoot ARRIRAW on an Alexa Mini it isn't required as that flavour of ARRIRAW is in a .mxf File Container which works natively on Mac as opposed to the .ari File Container. If you ever find yourself using a <a href="https://codex.online/products/vault-hardware/xl-series" target="_blank" title="Codex Vault" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex Vault</a> you'll need this software to interface with the hardware. You'll need to sign up for a free Codex Account to download this software.<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://codex.online/software" target="_blank" title="Codex Software" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CodexVault_grande.jpg?v=1524533195" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="http://www.red.com/products/redcine-x-pro" target="_blank" title="REDCINE-X" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">REDCINE-X</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">This is the all-in-one RED Toolkit from RED Digital Cinema. While you can playback R3D Files in a number of different softwares this is still my go to when dealing with RED Footage. It allows you to transcode, quality control check and apply colour correction to your footage. It's optimised to work with RED RAW from any RED Camera, it should be in your kit hands down.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.red.com/products/redcine-x-pro" target="_blank" title="REDCINE-X" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/RedCineX_grande.jpg?v=1524533886" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/blackmagic-disk-speed-test/id425264550?mt=12" target="_blank" title="Blackmagic Disk Speed Test" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">BLACKMAGIC DISK SPEED TEST</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Running a disk speed test is a daily occurrence for Data Wranglers. Everytime I get a new hard drive I will run a disk speed test on it before I use it, that way I can verify that it is running correctly at the speeds that I expect. When you have an offload performing slow this is an invaluable tool for troubleshooting. Super simple in design but it's solid as a rock. A must have for your toolkit.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/au/app/blackmagic-disk-speed-test/id425264550?mt=12" target="_blank" title="Blackmagic Disk Speed Test" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/DiskSpeedTest_grande.jpg?v=1524533170" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://bjango.com/mac/istatmenus/" target="_blank" title="iStat Menus" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">iSTAT MENUS</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">One of my favorite utilities. Basically it displays your computer's vitals in the task bar so you can check them at a glance. It's highly customisable so you'll be able to tweak it to best suit you. I use this to check my CPU/GPU performance during transcoding, to monitor Hard Drive Read/Write Speeds during offloads, to look over my Data Speeds for Uploads/Downloads online and to quickly check CPU/GPU Temperatures when I'm demanding lots from my system such as transcoding or just working in hot environments.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://bjango.com/mac/istatmenus/" target="_blank" title="iStat Menus" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/iStatMenus_grande.jpg?v=1524533175" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://filmdrives.com/pages/label-maker" target="_blank" title="Label Maker" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">LABEL MAKER</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">At the core of every good data management process is organisation. This tool was custom built for making beautiful hard drives labels in record time. I use it to colour code my hard drives for easy identification, it let's me label drives with job name and job number as well as putting client and production logos on there which always goes down a treat with my clients.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://filmdrives.com/pages/label-maker" target="_blank" title="Label Maker" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/LabelMaker_grande.jpg?v=1524533887" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="http://www.arri.com/camera/alexa/tools/arriraw_converter/" target="_blank" title="ARRIRAW Converter" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">ARRIRAW CONVERTOR</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">This is ARRIs Propriety Software for dealing with ARRIRAW from an Alexa XT, SXT or LF. It used to be the bees knees for playing back ARRIRAW on your computer but I often found that it sometimes didn't work in which case I'd use <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">Resolve</a> instead. Now days I just use <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">Resolve</a> exclusively but it's nice to have a backup for playing ARRIRAW should I encounter some form of issue with <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">Resolve</a> while on a job.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.arri.com/camera/alexa/tools/arriraw_converter/" target="_blank" title="ARRIRAW Converter" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ARRIRAWConverter_grande.jpg?v=1524533194" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="http://www.arri.com/camera/amira/tools/arri_color_tool/" target="_blank" title="ARRI Color Tool" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">ARRI COLOR TOOL</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">This is a great piece of software that will allow you to convert a 3D LUT .cube File to an ARRI LOOK File which can be used with any Alexa or Amira Camera. This comes into play a lot on-set when a DP has a LUT that they want to toggle on/off in the camera. They give you the LUT as a .cube, you convert it to a LOOK with this tool and then transfer it to the camera via USB/SD Card. Very handy to have.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.arri.com/camera/amira/tools/arri_color_tool/" target="_blank" title="ARRI Color Tool" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ARRIColorTool_grande.jpg?v=1524533887" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="http://www.arri.com/camera/alexa/tools/arri_meta_extract/" target="_blank" title="ARRI Meta Extract" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">ARRI META EXTRACT</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">This is a tool to extract metadata from footage that has been shot on any flavour of Alexa Camera. It's mainly intended to be a Post-Production Tool but I have found that it can be handy on-set every now and then for pretty niche purposes. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">One job didn't have any camera sheets from Shoot Day 01 and we needed to match a shot on Shoot Day 02, the focus puller had an idea of the distances but couldn't quite remember. As we were using an Alexa Mini with a WCU-4 I was able to find the shot and extract the metadata where I found the focus data, which I then interpreted into feet and inches and was able to confirm the exact focus distances for that shot. Pretty cool.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Use for this software won't come up all the time but it can be super handy from time to time.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.arri.com/camera/alexa/tools/arri_meta_extract/" target="_blank" title="ARRI Meta Extract" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ARRIMetaExtract_grande.jpg?v=1524533193" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="http://www.arri.com/camera/alexa/tools/arri_frameline_composer/" target="_blank" title="ARRI Frame Line Composer" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">ARRI FRAMELINE COMPOSER</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential Web Tool)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">This isn't software that you download to your computer, it's online software that can be accessed from the web on any computer. It's used to generate custom framelines for any Alexa Camera. I use this all the time. There is always a request for custom shading or for specific framelines that aren't standard. You'll hear 'Give me a 1:1 Frameline for social' or 'Can I get 2.40:1 Framelines in 4:3 Sensor Mode with 50% Shading?'. Nothing to download, just know it exists and be familiar with how it works.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.arri.com/camera/alexa/tools/arri_frameline_composer/" target="_blank" title="ARRI Frame Line Composer" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/ARRIFLC_grande.jpg?v=1524534158" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/premiere.html" target="_blank" title="Premiere Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">ADOBE PREMIERE PRO</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/premiere.html" target="_blank" title="Premiere Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Premiere Pro</a> is a popular editing software used by editors in the industry. It's incredibly versatile and performs well. Sometimes you may encounter a really weird file format that none of your other software will open, try <a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/premiere.html" target="_blank" title="Premiere Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Premiere</a>, it almost never fails. If you ever get asked for a quick edit from a Director or DP now you can effortlessly deliver. Not essential but definitely a valuable tool for your kit.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/premiere.html" target="_blank" title="Premiere Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Premiere_grande.jpg?v=1524533191" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/media-encoder.html" target="_blank" title="Media Encoder" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">ADOBE MEDIA ENCODER</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">While I use <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">DaVinci Resolve</a> for most of my transcoding I still find <a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/media-encoder.html" target="_blank" title="Media Encoder" rel="noopener noreferrer">Media Encoder</a> to be a great backup option. Just as <a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/premiere.html" target="_blank" title="Premiere Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Premiere</a> is great at reading weird file formats, <a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/media-encoder.html" target="_blank" title="Media Encoder" rel="noopener noreferrer">Media Encoder</a> is great at exporting to weird file formats. I have used it quite extensively over the past year for doing HEVC (H.265) Transcodes which <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/au/products/davinciresolve/" target="_blank" title="DaVinci Resolve" rel="noopener noreferrer">Resolve</a> doesn't support. For me it's essential, for you I think it'd prove handy.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/media-encoder.html" target="_blank" title="Media Encoder" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/MediaEncoder_grande.jpg?v=1524533181" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/aftereffects.html" target="_blank" title="After Effects" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">ADOBE AFTER EFFECTS</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Many times I've been on a Green Screen Shoot without VTR and the question has come up 'Can you just do a quick test key on this please?'. My answer is 'Absolutely!'. I can import rushes into AE and do a quick key with <a href="https://helpx.adobe.com/after-effects/using/keying.html" target="_blank" title="KeyLight" rel="noopener noreferrer">KeyLight</a>. I'm no Green Screen Wizard but this is generally more than enough to give whoever is asking peace of mind that their key is going to work.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/aftereffects.html" target="_blank" title="After Effects" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/AfterEffects_grande.jpg?v=1524533187" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/photoshop.html" target="_blank" title="Photoshop" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">ADOBE PHOTOSHOP</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/photoshop.html" target="_blank" title="Photoshop" rel="noopener noreferrer">Photoshop</a> is my go to tool for a lot of things. In the world where stills, graphics and video crossover all the time I find having <a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/photoshop.html" target="_blank" title="Photoshop" rel="noopener noreferrer">Photoshop</a> super handy. I used to use it to make my Hard Drive Labels before <a href="https://filmdrives.com/pages/label-maker" target="_blank" title="Label Maker" rel="noopener noreferrer">Label Maker</a> came along, I still use it for slate covers and many other graphic and image manipulation tasks.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.adobe.com/au/products/photoshop.html" target="_blank" title="Photoshop" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Photoshop_grande.jpg?v=1524533182" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="http://www.i-funbox.com/" target="_blank" title="iFunBox" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">iFUN BOX</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">This is software for looking at data that is directly on your iPhone. Why is this included in my Data Kit you ask? Well, I've had jobs where a Director will shoot some additional footage on their iPhone that is intended to be cut in with the actual TVC. They ask me to wrangle it, no worries, this software makes it easy. It allows you to look at your iPhone Camera Roll and copy specific clips to your computer or the drives. While it doesn't do the checksums that you'd come to expect in a professional data wrangling environment it gives you reliable data transfer speeds and guarantees no loss of quality from the original media.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.i-funbox.com/" target="_blank" title="iFunBox" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/iFunBox_grande.jpg?v=1524533887" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #000000;">ACCESSORIES</span></strong></h1>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">CARD READERS</span></strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">There are two ways to look at Card Readers. They are provided by either the 'Camera Rental House' or the 'Data Wrangler'. I sit somewhere in the middle. High-End Card Readers should be provided by the Camera Rental House, this includes the <a href="https://codex.online/products/media-stations/capture-drive-dock-thunderbolt" title="Codex TB Reader" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex Mag Readers</a>, <a href="https://codex.online/products/media-stations/cfast2-reader" target="_blank" title="Codex CFast Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex CFast Readers</a>, <a href="http://www.red.com/store/products/red-station-redmag-18-mini" target="_blank" title="REDMAG Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">RED Mag Readers</a>, <a href="https://store.sony.com.au/archived-professional-storage/MRWE90.html" target="_blank" title="XQD Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">XQD Card Readers</a>, etc. Card Readers that the Data Wrangler could have in their kit include SD/CF Card Reader, SxS Card Reader, CFast Card Reader. I'll outline what is in my kit below.</span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">SD/CF CARD READER</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">The main reason to have an SD/CF Card Reader in your kit is to copy sound cards. Almost every Sound Recordist will record to either an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secure_Digital" target="_blank" title="SD Card" rel="noopener noreferrer">SD Card</a> or a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CompactFlash" target="_blank" title="CF Card" rel="noopener noreferrer">CF Card</a> and you should have a reliable way to read it on your system. Some MacBook Pros have an SD Card Slot on the side, this isn't as fast as a USB3.0 SD/CF Card Reader. So even if you have an in-built SD Card Reader you should still get an external one as it's faster, it will allow you to read CF Cards and then your internal reader will serve as a backup. Also, if you find yourself shooting on a DSLR that uses SD/CF you also have a Card Reader ready to go in your kit. It's not just for sound, it's for camera too.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Is use this <a href="http://www.lexar.com/portfolio_page/professional-usb-3-0-dual-slot-reader/" target="_blank" title="Lexar SD/CF Card Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lexar USB3.0 SD/CF Card Reader</a>. I've had it for years and it's never skipped a beat. The speeds are good and it's reliable. Plus the click up, click down actuation mechanism is amazing!<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.lexar.com/portfolio_page/professional-usb-3-0-dual-slot-reader/" target="_blank" title="Lexar SD/CF Card Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SDCardReader_grande.jpg?v=1524369599" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">SxS CARD READER</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">While the humble <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SxS" target="_blank" title="SxS Card" rel="noopener noreferrer">SxS Card</a> is fairly dated now, having an SxS Reader in my kit is something that I consider standard. It spawned back in the day when the Alexa Classic recorded to SxS Cards, all rental houses in Melbourne would send out the Sony USB2.0 SxS Card Reader with the kit which was very slow. To combat that all of us Data Wranglers purchased a <a href="https://www.sonnettech.com/es/product/echoexpresscard34thunderbolt.html" target="_blank" title="Sonnet SxS Card Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sonnet Thunderbolt SxS Pro Card Reader</a> which improved offload speeds considerably. Nowadays Sony has a <a href="http://www.lemac.com.au/Products/SonySxSPROSxS-1USB30CardReaderWriter.aspx" target="_blank" title="Sony SxS Card Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">USB3.0 SxS Card Reader</a> which may or may not come with your camera kit. In my eyes it's much better to have your own, if it doesn't get used it serves as a backup.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.sonnettech.com/es/product/echoexpresscard34thunderbolt.html" target="_blank" title="SxS Card Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SxSReader_grande.jpg?v=1524369601" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">CFAST 2.0 CARD READER</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">I never used to have a CFast Card Reader in my kit, then one day I was on a job and had a <a href="https://codex.online/products/media-stations/cfast2-reader" target="_blank" title="Codex CFast Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex CFast Reader</a> fail on me. Fortunately the rental house could send out a replacement on that same day but it took 2 Hours which set me back significantly. I'll never let that happen again so I purchased my own CFast Reader for my kit which has come in handy many times since.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">I have the <a href="https://www.videoguys.com.au/Shop/p/39125/lexar-cfast-2-0-thunderbolt-usb-3-0-reader-for-workflow-lrwcr2tbna.html" target="_blank" title="Lexar CFast Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lexar CFast Reader</a> which boasts both USB3.0 and Thunderbolt.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Your other option is the <a href="https://www.sandisk.com.au/home/memory-cards/memory-card-readers/extremepro-cfast20-reader-writer" target="_blank" title="SanDisk CFast Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">SanDisk CFast Card Reader</a>.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.videoguys.com.au/Shop/p/39125/lexar-cfast-2-0-thunderbolt-usb-3-0-reader-for-workflow-lrwcr2tbna.html" target="_blank" title="Lexar CFast Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CFastCardReader_grande.jpg?v=1524369598" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">ADAPTERS</span></strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">No matter what flavour of MacBook Pro you are using you'll likely need to include adapters in your Data Kit.</span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<a href="http://www.kanex.com/thunderbolt-esata" target="_blank" title="Kanex Adapter" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">KANEX THUNDERBOLT TO USB3.0 ADAPTER</span></strong></a><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">These are amazing adapters. They allow you to turn a Thunderbolt 1/2 Port into a USB3.0 Port. I am a firm believer in running each Card Reader/Drive on a separate bus or computer port, this adapter allows me to do that even with 3x USB3.0 Devices. I ended up buying two which let's me turn my <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/macbook-pro-retina-display-faq/" target="_blank" title="Old MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">Old Style MacBook Pro</a> into a system that has 4x USB3.0 Ports, I've used this on many jobs where the client wanted me to backup to 3x USB3.0 Hard Drives from a <a href="https://codex.online/products/media-stations/cfast2-reader" target="_blank" title="Codex CFast Reader" rel="noopener noreferrer">Codex USB3.0 CFast Card Reader</a>. Nothing in your kit should slow data management down, these adapters are absolutely essential.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.kanex.com/thunderbolt-esata" target="_blank" title="Kanex Adapter" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/KanexAdapters_grande.jpg?v=1524527154" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">APPLE THUNDERBOLT ADAPTERS</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">If you need to convert one port to another I have found the Apple Adapters to be very reliable. Even though I don't have a <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/macbook_pro/macbook-pro-touch-bar-faq/" target="_blank" title="New MacBook Pro" rel="noopener noreferrer">New Style MacBook Pro</a> I still carry newer adapters so that I can be equipped to handle any situation that arises.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">I have the following in my kit:</span><br><span style="color: #444444;"><a href="https://www.apple.com/au/shop/product/MMEL2AM/A/thunderbolt-3-usb-c-to-thunderbolt-2-adapter?fnode=f849db44800fbd8d92fb98f7e414bd62e657debce26e23224f212fc9cc683158a05a9f5d1422ffc4ac493c19826f79de9b6458c68afd7effaf4f7f9ee8c0fc914db1572eebcc0f3a350c8c4e751aa256a2f097a3b0cea82bcf007923b7282df4" target="_blank" title="USB-C to TB3" rel="noopener noreferrer">USB-C to THUNDERBOLT 3</a> x2</span><br><a href="https://www.apple.com/au/shop/product/MJ1M2AM/A/usb-c-to-usb-adapter?fnode=f849db44800fbd8d92fb98f7e414bd62e657debce26e23224f212fc9cc683158a05a9f5d1422ffc4ac493c19826f79de9b6458c68afd7effaf4f7f9ee8c0fc914db1572eebcc0f3a350c8c4e751aa256a2f097a3b0cea82bcf007923b7282df4" target="_blank" title="USB-C to USB-A" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="color: #444444;">USB-C to USB TYPE-A</span></a><br><a href="https://www.apple.com/au/shop/product/MD464ZM/A/apple-thunderbolt-to-firewire-adapter?fnode=f849db44800fbd8d92fb98f7e414bd62e657debce26e23224f212fc9cc683158a05a9f5d1422ffc4ac493c19826f79de9b6458c68afd7effaf4f7f9ee8c0fc914db1572eebcc0f3a350c8c4e751aa256a2f097a3b0cea82bcf007923b7282df4" target="_blank" title="TB2 to FW800" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="color: #444444;">THUNDERBOLT 2 to FIREWIRE 800</span></a><br><a href="https://www.apple.com/au/shop/product/MD463ZM/A/thunderbolt-to-gigabit-ethernet-adapter?fnode=0ee4eae968f46fbb34449c685980bbfd4d6adf1f3fc0c79286bb9afae2eea0d6ba6a42422e1228535dc11c6f9c774e224e5dcc6c3ad67f42d485144cfbf77d711727600c8a328e38f557a439036e6c3f373cf96832440482a6dec05f03260422" target="_blank" title="TB2 to ETHERNET" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="color: #444444;">THUNDERBOLT 2 to ETHERNET</span></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/AppleAdapters_grande.jpg?v=1524527857" alt=""></span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">SD TO MicroSD ADAPTERS</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">I have many of these in my kit. They allow me to copy footage from a MicroSD Card via my SD Card Reader should I need to. Super handy if you get a <a href="https://shop.gopro.com/APAC/cameras/" target="_blank" title="GoPro" rel="noopener noreferrer">GoPro</a> or something similar thrown into the mix.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/SDAdapters_grande.jpg?v=1524527858" alt=""></span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">CABLES</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Without a hard wired cable connection you can't wrangle data. You need cables. You need spare cables. You need all flavours of cable so that no matter the connection, no matter the interface, you've got something that will work. These are the cables I have in my kit that aren't bundled with card readers:</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">USB-C to USB-C CABLE x2</span><br><span style="color: #444444;">STANDARD USB3.0 CABLE x6</span><br><span style="color: #444444;">1M THUNDERBOLT CABLE </span><br><span style="color: #444444;">eSATA CABLE</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/USB3Cables_grande.jpg?v=1524527156" alt=""></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">GIGABIT ETHERNET CABLE x2</span><br><span style="color: #444444;">FW800 to FW800 CABLE</span><br><span style="color: #444444;">FW800 to FW400 CABLE</span><br><span style="color: #444444;">FW400 to FW400 CABLE</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/FWCables_grande.jpg?v=1524527155" alt=""></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">USB 2.0 TYPE-A to USB 2.0 TYPE-B CABLE</span><br><span style="color: #444444;">USB 2.0 to MINI-USB</span><br><span style="color: #444444;">USB 2.0 to MICRO-USB</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/USB2Cables_grande.jpg?v=1524527159" alt=""></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Have a lot of cables. Have spares. Be prepared.</span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">OTHER</span></strong></h3>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">LAPTOP CHARGER</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">You'll get a charger with your laptop. Make sure it's in your kit at all times. Ideally carry a spare. If your laptop has no power you can't wrangle data. I originally only traveled with one charger, then it broke so I purchased a replacement and repaired the old one. Now I use the old charger as a spare. Sometimes I set it up in my van with a car inverter to keep my rig running while in transit.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Chargers_grande.jpg?v=1524527858" alt=""></span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">CAR INVERTER</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">As I've said before 'If your laptop has no power you can't wrangle data'. Some jobs will be run and gun, constantly moving from location to location, it's easy to get stitched up. An inverter will help mitigate that risk. It doesn't need to be a huge inverter as it's only charging your laptop which usually draws around 85W. This will help you stay charged throughout the day even with ten location moves!</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/CarInverter_grande.jpg?v=1524368707" alt=""></span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">LABEL MAKER</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">While these days I prefer to make high quality labels using <a href="https://filmdrives.com/pages/label-maker" target="_blank" title="Label Maker" rel="noopener noreferrer">Label Maker</a> I still carry a <a href="http://www.dymo.com/en-AU" target="_blank" title="Dymo Labellers" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dymo Labeller</a> in my kit as a spare, my model is a <a href="https://www.officeworks.com.au/shop/officeworks/p/dymo-letratag-100h-handheld-label-maker-blue-sasd25630" target="_blank" title="LetraTag 100H" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dymo LetraTag 100H</a>. This comes in handy from time to time for labeling drives or other miscellaneous things on-set. You could also go a <a href="https://www.brother.com.au/p-touch-labellers" target="_blank" title="P-Touch" rel="noopener noreferrer">P-Touch Labeller</a> which is also quite popular.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.dymo.com/en-AU" target="_blank" title="Dymo Labellers" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/DymoLabelMaker_grande.jpg?v=1524527163" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">USB3.0 THUMB DRIVES</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Often you'll need to quickly copy a small file here or there. You might have a Production Manager asking if you've got a USB Stick. It's easy to grab a few USB Thumb Drives for your kit so you've got a quick way to solve these problems when they arise. Definitely recommended.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/USBThumbDrives_grande.jpg?v=1524527153" alt=""></span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">HARD DRIVE DOCKING STATION</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">You definitely don't need one of these in your Data Kit, it's just a nice safety to have. I carry it as a fail safe to help troubleshoot drives. If I have a hard drive fail and want to investigate further I can use this to mount the bare bones SATA Drive and see if it reads thus determining if the problem is with the drive itself or the enclosure. Also if I'm dealing with RAID Drives, sometimes RAID Arrays with 5 Drives will have a problem and I'll need to look at one drive individually, this is the tool that allows me to do that.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">I use a <a href="https://www.macfixit.com.au/newertech-voyager-q-quad-interface-firewire-800-400-usb-3-0-esata-sata-i-ii-iii-hard-drive-docking-solution/" target="_blank" title="VoyagerQ HDD Docking Station" rel="noopener noreferrer">VoyagerQ HDD Docking Station</a> which sports USB3.0, FW800 and eSATA Connection. It requires external power to run and ships with a power adapter.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.macfixit.com.au/newertech-voyager-q-quad-interface-firewire-800-400-usb-3-0-esata-sata-i-ii-iii-hard-drive-docking-solution/" target="_blank" title="VoyagerQ HDD Docking Station" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/HDDDockingStation_grande.jpg?v=1524527155" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">iPHONE CHARGERS</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">What do all people on-set use everyday? Their phones! They always die and one of my most asked questions is 'Do you have an iPhone charger?'. So I started carrying iPhone Chargers in my kit. I have one 10W Charger for iPads and one 5W Charger for iPhones. I also carry the old school 30-Pin Charge Cable as well as multiple Lightning Charge Cables. If you throw in a Micro USB Cable you can charge most Android Phones as well. Be a hero, carry a phone charger in your kit!</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/iPhoneChargers_grande.jpg?v=1524527154" alt=""></span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">POWER BANKS</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">If you want to one-up your service have a power bank or two in your kit. That way if someone asks for a charger you can offer a portable option as well. I don't use mine that often but it has come in handy many times.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">One time in particular we were on a Movi all day using the <a href="https://www.abelcine.com/articles/blog-and-knowledge/tutorials-and-guides/alexa-mini-quick-tip-remote-control-via-wi-fi" target="_blank" title="Alexa Mini WIFI Control" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alexa Mini WIFI Control on iPhone</a>, the 1st ACs phone was close to dying which would have caught us out, I brought out my Power Bank and a Cable and we were good to go for the rest of the day. Not essential but a nice addition to the kit.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/PowerBank_grande.jpg?v=1524527162" alt=""></span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">DOUBLE ADAPTER<br></span></strong><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">These are great if you need to add just one more bank of power to your UPS or if you need to split off power and share with someone else. Ties in again with having your own power infrastructure for on-set data wrangling.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/DoubleAdapter_grande.jpg?v=1524527160" alt=""></span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">USB MOUSE</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Optional)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Funny story behind this mouse. One time on a job I had someone spill water on my laptop. They didn't tell me about it either, I went back to put on the next card and found water all over the trackpad. I immediately soaked it all up but something was wrong, the trackpad didn't work. Thankfully everything else functioned but I was unable to wrangle data as I couldn't interact with my computer due to the damaged trackpad. Luckily someone had a spare mouse which I plugged in to control my computer and that got me through the day. Now I carry my own spare just encase this very rare instance happens again.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Mouse_grande.jpg?v=1524527157" alt=""></span></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">
<strong><span style="color: #444444;">BACKPACK</span></strong><br><em><strong><span style="color: #444444;">(Essential)</span></strong></em>
</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Last but not least, the backpack! How on earth do you carry all of this stuff around? Well, you have a few options. Some people like an over the shoulder laptop bag, others like Pelican Cases, me, I prefer a backpack. Currently I am running an old <a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/292331-REG/Lowepro_LP34030_PEF_CompuTrekker_AW_Backpack.html" target="_blank" title="CompuTrekker AW" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lowepro CompuTrekker AW</a> which I've used the past couple of years. Soon I plan on moving over to a <a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/1244085-REG/accessory_power_grsls17100bkew_usa_gear_s17_dslr.html" target="_blank" title="USA Gear Backpack" rel="noopener noreferrer">USA Gear S17 DSLR Camera Backpack</a>. The most important thing is to make sure you have a spit for your laptop and a whole bunch of compartments. Compartments allow organisation which is key to laying out an efficient data management kit.<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/292331-REG/Lowepro_LP34030_PEF_CompuTrekker_AW_Backpack.html" target="_blank" title="CompuTrekker AW" rel="noopener noreferrer" style="border: none;"><span style="color: #444444;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/2691/1130/files/Backpack_grande.jpg?v=1524541120" alt=""></span></a></p>
<h1 style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="color: #444444;">CONCLUSION</span></strong></h1>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">It's often daunting to figure out what you need when building a Data Kit. Thankfully I've managed data in almost every situation imaginable and have developed quite an understanding for what tools you will need. If you equip yourself with the tools listed above and you know how to use them you will be fully sorted on-set 99% of the time.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Do you have other super helpful tools in your Data Kit? I'd love to hear about them. Please let me know in the comments section below.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Same goes for questions, please reach out in the comments below and I'll do my best to help.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #444444;">Thanks! I hope this guide has been useful to you!</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
